<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The certainty of heavenly and the uncertainty of earthly treasures together with a discovery where the treasure and heart is placed / as it was delivered in severall sermons by that eminently faithfull servant of Christ, Mr. William Strong ...</title>
            <author>Strong, William, d. 1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 104 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61776</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5998</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13546085</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13546085</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100129</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61776)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100129)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1558:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The certainty of heavenly and the uncertainty of earthly treasures together with a discovery where the treasure and heart is placed / as it was delivered in severall sermons by that eminently faithfull servant of Christ, Mr. William Strong ...</title>
                  <author>Strong, William, d. 1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 204 [i.e. 203] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Wilson ... and are to be sold by Francis Tyton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages torn with loss of imprint date.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: New College (University of Edinburgh). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew VI, 20-21 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100129:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100129:1"/>
            <p>The Certainty of <hi>Heavenly,</hi> AND The Uncertainty of <hi>Earthly</hi> TREASURES.</p>
            <p>Together with a Diſcovery where the Treaſure and Heart is placed.</p>
            <p>As it was Delivered in ſeverall Sermons, By that Eminently Faithfull ſervant of Chriſt, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>William Strong,</hi> late Miniſter at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They being his laſt Sermons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Wilſon</hi> living in <hi>Well-yard</hi> neere <hi>Weſt-Smithfield,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Francis Tyton</hi> at the Three Daggers ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re the Inner Temple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:100129:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100129:2"/>
            <head>The certainty of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, and the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of Earthly Treaſures.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Math. 6.20, 21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Lay up for your ſelves Treaſures in Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For where your Treaſure is, there will your heart be alſo.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe words there are two things; Firſt a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures below; Secondly, an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, in References to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100129:3"/>Treaſures above; Both theſe branches have two things at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending them. The Dehorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from laying up Treaſures below, lies in two Arguments: 1. their uncertainty, 2. their decay. The Exhortation for laying up Treaſure in Heaven lies alſo in two arguments: 1. Their Stability. 2. Their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance. The uncertainty of the one, and the certainty of the other; the decay of the one, and the durableneſſe of the other, ſhould cauſe us to treaſure up the one, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteem the other. Then the ſecond part of the text comes in as a reaſon to enforce the former, <hi>For where your Treaſure is, there will your hearts be alſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of this Text, I ſhall lay down two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100129:3"/>to treat upon.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That every man hath a Treaſure in this life;</hi> For he doth ſpeak it as an Act performed in this life, and not as an Act to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the life to come: this life is the ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time, that life is the Reaping time; Here the Treaſure is in getting, there it is in ſpending, therefore every mans Treaſure is in this life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That whereſoever the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, it is Attractive to draw the heart unto it.</hi> Or thus, <hi>Every man laies up his heart where hee laies up his Treaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To begin with the firſt Doctrine, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> Every man hath a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in this life.</note> namely</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 1 That every man hath a Treaſure in this life.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100129:4"/>
            <p>There are (for the explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this truth) two ſorts of Treaſures. Firſt, God hath his Treaſures; Secondly, men have their Treaſures.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <note place="margin">Gods Treaſure are</note> God hath his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: The Treaſures of God are of four ſorts.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Of Nature.</note> The Treaſures of Nature, <hi>Job</hi> 38.22. <hi>Haſt thou entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Treaſures of the Snow? or haſt thou ſeen the Treaſures of the Hail?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> The Treaſures of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Whoſe belly thou filleſt with thy hid Treaſures;</hi> 'Tis ſpoken in Reference to ungodly men, ſome there are that have in Common Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence their bellies fill'd with hid Treaſure. Godly men they have the beſt of the dainties of Providence, but ungodly ones what they have, is but to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100129:4"/>ſatisfie their belly, never fills their Souls, their Soules are left empty of grace, though their bellies are filled with hid Treaſure.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Of Grace</note> There are Treaſures of Grace, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3. <hi>In him are hid all the Treaſures of Wiſdome and Knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">Of wrath and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</note> There are Treaſures of wrath &amp; vengeance in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.34. <hi>It is ſealed up among my Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: to me belongs vengeance,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe are Gods Treaſures the Scripture ſpeaks of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <note n="2" place="margin">Men have their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</note> men have their Treaſures; And that which a man makes his chief good, that is his Treaſure, that which he placeth his happineſſe in, that which the comfort of his life flowes from, that is mans Treaſure; ſee it ſo in thoſe two Scriptures, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100129:5"/>
               <hi>Pſ.</hi> 17.14. That which in this place is called a Treaſure, is there called, <hi>His good things, and his portion;</hi> that is, that which a man makes his chiefe good. The greateſt difference between Godly men, and the men of this world is this; the one is all for great proviſions in the way, and nothing for the Journeies end; the other is for all at the Journeyes end, and but little in the way.</p>
            <p>For the opening of this Doctrine further, that every man in this life hath his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and his own Treaſure, this take in four propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Every man hath ſome chiefe good.</note> That every man hath ſome chiefe good which his Soul is ſet upon, and which it centers in, wherein he placeth his happineſſe, which if you
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100129:5"/>could attain perfectly, your Soules would be at reſt. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.7. <hi>Return unto thy reſt O my Soul.</hi> Godly men have their Treaſure in Heaven, God is their Treaſure, God is their Portion, therefore they can rejoyce and ſay, God is my chiefeſt good and my utmoſt end. <hi>David</hi> tells you the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of his ſoul ran after God; <hi>My ſoul thirſteth for God, the living God,</hi> all this is to ſhew that God is <hi>Davids</hi> chief good, untill the Soule can at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to its chiefeſt good its ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver at reſt: But take a poore carnall wretch that never knew any thing above the Creature, becauſe the creature is his chief good, till hee can obtain it, he is reſtleſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6. unto 14. <hi>verſe.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.29. Ungodly mens ſoules goe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100129:6"/>wholly after their treaſure, and a godly mans ſoul goes wholly after his God; <hi>Davids</hi> ſoule 'tis ſaid, <hi>was bound up in the bundle of life with the Lord his God;</hi> but it followes, a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mans ſoul <hi>is ſlung away from God, as out of the middle of a ſling.</hi> There are three things in that ſling. 1. It notes a diſtance from God, as the ſtone in the ſling is at a diſtance from the man. 2. It notes not onely a diſtance from God, but it notes a diſtance in judgement, in wrath; he will ſling away the wicked from the middeſt of his people, he will ſeparate them from himſelf in wrath. 3. It notes violence, ſlinging is a violent motion.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Every man chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſome chiefe good in this life.</note> 
               <hi>Propoſition.</hi> Every man hath ſome good in this life in regard of Election, not in regard
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100129:6"/>of Fruition; ſome chief good he chooſeth in this life, for the chief good of the Saints is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for them for the life to come: the Election is below, the Fruition is above; the one hath his portion in this life, the other in the life to come. Some have choſen vanity; now that you have choſen here, you will enjoy hereafter; ſome of you chuſe Riches, that which you chuſe here, will be your portion hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; that which is your chief good in this life, you muſt content your ſelves to have in the life to come.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Every man hath his owne chief good.</note> Every man in this life hath his own chief good, and that is his Treaſure: That which is another mans chief good, is not thine: As every man lives by his own Faith ſo every man
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100129:7"/>lives upon his own Treaſure: thy Faith perhaps is thy Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and God is thy Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, an other mans Riches are his Treaſure: ſee a godly mans Treaſure, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 33.6. <hi>The feare of the Lord is his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure:</hi> this is peculiarly ſpoken of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and in him of the Church of God; Now what is here meant by <hi>the fear of God? Calvin</hi> notes two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Reverential fear and awe of the Majeſtie of God, from a right apprehenſion of his Righteouſneſſe and Holineſſe, ſo <hi>Prov.</hi> 17. <hi>The feare of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. By <hi>Fear,</hi> is meant an awe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful worſhip of God, <hi>Worſhip the Lord with fear, and rejoyce with trembling.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 2.11</note> Thus you ſee what was <hi>Hezekiah's</hi> Treaſure, <hi>It was the feare of the Lord;</hi> a holy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100129:7"/>feare of God, and a conſtant worſhip of him is a Chriſtians Treaſure.</p>
            <p>But how comes it to paſſe, that every man hath his own Treaſure?</p>
            <p n="1">1. From the different lights that men have; <note place="margin">Men have dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent lights</note> ſome can ſee good in that which an other man can ſee none, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. <hi>We look not at the things which are ſeen, but at the things which are not ſeen, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.4</note> There are ſome in whom the God of this world hath blinded their eyes, and ſome the eyes of whoſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding are enlightned. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 1.17.18. Men have different good things, becauſe they have different lights; the things of this life are baſe in the eyes of ſome, though glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to others.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Men have dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours.</note> Men have different trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100129:8"/>to themſelves, becauſe they have different Savours, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5. <hi>For they that are after the fleſh, do mind the things of the fleſh; but they that are after the ſpirit, the things of the ſpirit:</hi> the meaning is, they ſavour the things of the fleſh. Tell a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man of a promiſe, it hath no more ſavour to him, then a ſtock or a ſtone: tell a Rich man of a promiſe, who makes Riches his treaſure, this hath no ſavour in it; he can taſte ſweetneſſe in dainty meats, and in gorgeous appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, and in the pleaſures of ſin that are but for a ſeaſon: but let a Saint come and look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the word of God, thy word is <hi>ſweeter</hi> to me <hi>then the honey or the honey combe:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 19.10.</note> people runne after vanity, becauſe they ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour no better things.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100129:8"/>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Men make dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent choice.</note> From their choice: would you know why <hi>Iſrael</hi> was Gods peculiar treaſure, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God choſe them him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144.4. Some men make choice of God as their chiefeſt good, let him enjoy God he is contented; ſaith <hi>David, Whom have I in heaven but thee, there's none on earth whom I deſire in compariſon of thee:</hi> But if you let me live without God, 'tis nothing, he accounts all things nothing in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of God, becauſe that's the mans chief good: Take an other, He ſaith, I can live without God all my life time, and I can be content never to heare of God; the Reaſon is, becauſe they chuſe an other good for their chiefe good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides God himſelfe, this chief good is called a mans Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100129:9"/>you ſee now every man hath his chiefe good in this life, and his own chiefe good in this life.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">A mans chiefe good is his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> 
               <hi>Particular,</hi> That a mans chiefe good is his Treaſure, and that upon a three-fold Accompt.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Becauſe of the preciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> From the Preciouſneſſe of it; No man owns or eſteems his Treaſure, unleſſe it be his own chiefe good, and that which he eſteems as precious. A mans Treaſures are preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, therefore when the Lord ſpeaks of precious things, he calls them <hi>a Treaſure, Mat.</hi> 13.44.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. <hi>The Goſpel is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Treaſure,</hi> becauſe it carries precious things with it. Take a man whoſe chiefe good is God, take God from him and he is undone. But an other man who makes wealth his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100129:9"/>treaſure, he ſaith, take away this, and I ſhall have no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; one takes God for his treaſure, and the other wealth for his.</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis called Treaſure, <note place="margin">Plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</note> not onely for the preciouſneſſe of it, but for the plentifulneſſe of it; for 'tis not a little that will make a Treaſure, but abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3. <hi>In whom are hid all the Treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge:</hi> What ever is a mans chiefe good, he deſires it with an infinite appetite, for he is never ſatisfied. Take a man that makes pleaſure his chiefe treaſure, he is like a Horſe-leach, that cryes, <hi>give, give:</hi> let him have to day, yet he is hungry to morrow. Take a man whoſe chiefe good is laid up in God, though he have all the world can afford
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100129:10"/>him; yet he ſayes, give me more comfort from God, more Communion with God, and more likeneſſe to God; hee is ſtill unſatisfied, becauſe it's his chief good.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Valuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it.</note> 'Tis called a Treaſure becauſe it's that by which a man values himſelfe: look how much a man hath in his Treaſure, ſo much he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives he is worth: there is a Rate which the man puts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, it adds as it were to the value of himſelf. Now as men value themſelves according to their wealth, honor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo God values every man according to his heart. <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.20. <hi>The heart of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is little worth:</hi> the man is worth nothing if his heart be worth nothing. For theſe grounds 'tis called a Treaſure,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100129:10"/>for the preciouſneſſe, for the plentifullneſs, &amp; for the value and eſteem a man puts upon it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 1. For the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Of Examination: where is your treaſure? Take this rule, where thy love is, ther's thy heart; where thy heart is, ther's thy Treaſure; where thy Treaſure is, ther's thy Heaven, where thy heaven is, ther's thy God; and where thy God is, ther's thy happines.</p>
            <p>There are ſix things I would have you to conſider, <note place="margin">That is your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> as to this uſe of Examination, that you may know where your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure lies.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Which you la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour moſt for.</note> Conſider what it is that you dig for, that you labour for, that you are willing to ſpend your money for; this is the firſt try all of your Treaſure, If you dig for wiſdome as for preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones, <hi>If thou ſeek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100129:11"/>her as Silver, and ſearcheſt for her as for hid treaſures.</hi> Pro. 2.4. and ſaith our Saviour <hi>Job:</hi> 6.27. <hi>Labour not for the meat which periſheth, but for that meat which endureth unto everlaſting life?</hi> What's the great thing you work for in this life? What is it you lay out your money for? that you labour for? doſt thou lay out thy Knowledge for God? thy eſtate for God? or doſt thou ſpend thy money for that which is not bread, and labour for that which ſatisfieth not? <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 55.2. When a man ſhall return to his own heart, and ſay, <hi>I have laboured for Wealth all my daies, and wearied my ſelf for vanity, and now I come to die, I find that I have not laboured at all for God, I have not choſen God for my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure;</hi> Oh this mans condition
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100129:11"/>is very ſad! how many are there that can laviſh out their wealth upon their luſts; But let a poor member of Chriſt come, every penny that's gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them, is as much as a drop of blood: that which you lay out your money for, and digg for moſt, that's your Treaſure.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Which is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of your lives.</note> Examine what it is by which the comforts of your lives come in, what it is you live upon: whether you <hi>labour for the meat which periſheth, or for that which endureth to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting life?</hi> John 6.27. Whether your comforts come in by <hi>eating the bread of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and drinking the wine of violence.</hi> Prov. 4.17. Or by feeding upon Jeſus Chriſt by faith? Hee that feeds onely upon the Creature, <hi>feeds upon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100129:12"/>Aſhes, a deceived heart hath turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him aſide,</hi> Iſa. 44.20. That man that makes not God his treaſure, makes the Devil his Treaſure. Therefore conſider by what doth the Comfort of your lives come in? ſome may ſay, I live a comfortable life, becauſe I have a great deal of wealth, and a plentifull Table; but the other ſaith, I live a comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life, becauſe I have had Communion with God, and ſome taſt of Heavenly Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: that from whence the Comfort of your lives comes, in that's your Treaſure.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Which you are to keep.</note> What is that which is your greateſt care to keep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things elſe? that's your Treaſure. Treaſures are commonly hidden, that men may keep them ſafe: take a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100129:12"/>man that makes Riches his treaſure, what doth he feare moſt? theft: but take a godly man that makes God his Treaſure, what doth he fear moſt? ſinne, becauſe God is his Treaſure.</p>
            <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">Which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat unto.</note> What doth your ſoules retreat unto for comfort in any trouble, in any diſgrace, in any diſtreſſe? whither doe you retire? whither doth a rich man retire when hee is in danger? to his Riches; whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth a godly man retire when he is in danger; to his God; <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10, 11. <hi>the name of the Lord is a ſtrong Tower: the Righteous runneth into it, and are ſafe.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10.15.</note> The Rich mans wealth is his ſtrong City: and as an high wall in his owne conceit; one retires to his Riches, and the other to his God.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:100129:13"/>
            <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">Which you value men for.</note> How doe you judge of other men? for you value men more or leſſe according to that you count your owne treaſure. A godly man that makes Grace his treaſure; Ask him this queſtion, who is the beſt man? whether the rich man, or the godly man? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee that hath much of grace, or he that hath much of Gold? whether he that hath much of the Creature, or hee that hath moſt of Chriſt? Hee anſwers, the godly man is the better man, becauſe he ſeekes that which is pretious unto me, becauſe he ſeeks his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure above, ſaith <hi>David.</hi> Pſal. 16.3. <hi>To the excellent of the Earth, in whom is all my delight;</hi> Hee accounts them excellent becauſe they have much of that which he counts his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100129:13"/>and he values all other men according to that they have of that which hee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts his treaſure.</p>
            <p>6.<note n="6" place="margin">Which you prize time for.</note> What are the times that you do moſtly prize? A man u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually prizeth thoſe times moſt that bring him in moſt of his treaſure, moſt of his wealth, and profit <hi>Amos</hi> 8.12. ſay they, <hi>When will the Sabbath be gone?</hi> there was no day ſo tire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome unto them as a Sabbath day, they longed for the week daies, becauſe they brought them in much plenty, much of their treaſure. But now with a gracious heart it is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, as the one ſaith, <hi>when will the Sabbath be gone?</hi> ſo the other ſaith, <hi>When will the Sabbath come?</hi> Iſa. 38.13. they called it a <hi>delight,</hi> becauſe it brings in moſt of their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100129:14"/>So it is with a grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heart. Thoſe times wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he hath trading with Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, wherein he hath Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt, wherein he hath the powrings forth of the Spirit, wherein he hath the Exerciſe of Grace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee is made ſerviceable to God; theſe are the times that he accounts pretious.</p>
            <p>There are five Rules of tryall more, which every one ſhould take as looking-Glaſſes, wherein you you may ſee where your treaſure and chief good is laid up; <note place="margin">A mans treaſure is that.</note> which is the greateſt Queſtion to be reſolved that can be.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Which is firſt in his aim.</note> A mans treaſure and chief good is that which is firſt in his eye and aime in the whole bent and courſe of his life, that which hath the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100129:14"/>in all his intentions, that is his chief good. Intention is the bent and aime of the will in Reference to ſome good propounded to it, by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: that which is firſt in Intention, is laſt in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, if it be a good ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; but if it be a good to be obtained, then that which is firſt in Intention, is laſt in fruition; <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. <hi>Seek firſt the Kingdom of God,</hi> &amp;c. There is not onely a ſeeking of the Kingdom of Heaven, but there muſt be a ſeeking of it firſt; for God ſtands much on Priorities in Scripture; and if it be not ſet in its due order, God himſelf is diſpleaſed with it, and that which is done is, as if it had not been done at all. Take a naturall man whoſe chiefe good is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100129:15"/>wealth; it is firſt in his Eye, it hath a prehemenency in all his Actions and Intentions he ſeekes an Eſtate firſt to be great in the world, rather then to be good in the World; the chiefe good is that which draws out the firſt born of the Soul, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18. <hi>We look not at, or we ſeek not, the things that are ſeen, but at the things that are not ſeen,</hi> &amp;c. Hee ſpeaks not onely in his own name, but in behalf of all the Saints, for they have all one chiefe good and utmoſt end; <note place="margin">Phil. 3.14.</note> thus it was with <hi>Paul, I preſſe to the mark for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> I preſſe to the mark, the mark is that hee propoſeth, that he ſhoots at, as an Archer at his mark: you may ſee by this, what's your treaſure; what is the firſt and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100129:15"/>main thing in your Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for ther's no Saint in the World, but if God ſhould ſay, ask what thou wilt, and I will give it thee; he would ſay, firſt I deſire intereſt in they ſelfe, and Inheritance with the Saints: that which is firſt in Intention, is laſt in fruition, what the main of your ſouls is ſet upon, that is your chiefe good.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Why he deſires for it ſelf.</note> A man ſhall know where his treaſure and chiefe good lies by this; that's a mans chief good which hee deſires for it ſelf, deſires are all things elſe in ſubordination thereto; Chriſt gives you this rule in <hi>Mark</hi> 3.7. <hi>Hee that loves Father and Mother more then me, is not worthy of me:</hi> A man is bound to love Father and Mother, but not more then me; when
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100129:16"/>doth a man love any thing more then Chriſt? when it comes in competition with him, but not in ſubordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to him: God is to be belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for himſelf, and Chriſt is to be received for himſelf, and therefore 'tis ſaid, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.26. <hi>He that hates not Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>cannot be my Diſciple;</hi> how hates them? a man is bound to love them all. The Command is not abſolute, that he ſhould hate them ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, but comparatively; to hate them is to ſoe an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in Chriſt above them, Chriſt is to be beloved for himſelf, and God for himſelf. That Rule of <hi>Austin</hi> is true, we are to love friends in God, and Enemies for God. But how ſhall I know that I love God for himſelf? for a man
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100129:16"/>may love Chriſt and God from a principle of ſelf-love. I ſhall give you two try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls.</p>
            <p>Firſt, then a man loves God for himſelfe, when hee is willing to part with all things for him: that man that is willing to part with all things for God, muſt needs love God above all things. But how ſhall I know that I am willing to part with all for Gods ſake? there are two ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons when men are tryed in this life; at the time of Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the time of diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Firſt, At the time of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, <hi>Philipi.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Paul</hi> counts all things <hi>but droſſe and and dung that he may win Chriſt,</hi> ſo <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 14.33. <hi>he that forſakes not all, cannot be my Diſciple,</hi> The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is the time of Diſſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100129:17"/>without this I cannot at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to my chiefeſt good: will the Lord have an <hi>Iſaac?</hi> the ſoul will give him an <hi>Iſaac,</hi> he will ſacrifice his parts with all that ever he hath, and give them up to God, <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6.23.</note> 
               <hi>you are not your own, you are bought with a price,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle. A gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſoule hath experience of this at the time of diſſolution, when hee ſets all things here below aſide for God; when his friends, his Eſtate, his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and his portion take their leaves of him; A godly man when he comes to die, he can look on all theſe dying things rejoycingly; he can ſay, I have no need of them, <note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> Lord, <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better,</hi> Phil 1.23. as a Martyr ſaid when hee came to die, <hi>my friends are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100129:17"/>dear, my Children are dear, my Wife is dear, but my Chriſt is dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond triall that a man loves God for himſelfe; when a man doth abſtract God and Chriſt, the good that is in them, and the good that comes by them, and the ſoule is carried to them for the good that is in them. There are two ſeaſons when all the good that comes by Religion and godlineſs, ſeemes to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from it; at the time of Affliction, and at the time of deſertion.</p>
            <p>Firſt, At the time of affliction: Is there any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward benefit comes by Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in the time of perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and affliction?</p>
            <p>Secondly, All the time of deſertion that deprives a man
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100129:18"/>of all comfort; now when a man ſhall be able to fay as <hi>Job, though be kill me, yet I will truſt in him; I will love him for the excellency that hee hath in him, though I receive none of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency from him:</hi> For the good that comes by him, many love him, but for the good that is in him a gratious ſoule loves him. Take a man that makes riches his Treaſure, hee will part with a good Conſcience, the beſt friends he hath; nay, though hee act to the griefe of his friends, and to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of his Enemies; yet if the man doe but obtaine that which he deſires, he matters not; this is a clear argument: that a man loves it for it ſelfe. An ambitious man will break all bonds, Naturall, Civill, and Religious; yea, let him
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100129:18"/>be accounted an ambitious ſelf-ſeeking man; yea, let cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and Conſcience lie at the ſtake, yet hee will deſpiſe Counſell, tread upon friends, trample upon Lawes, and all that hee may be great in the world.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Unto which he refers all things.</note> That which is a mans Treaſure or his chiefe good, he referrs all things unto it, and ſeekes all things from it; for a mans chief good and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt end is that which works in all the reſt. I ſhall give you two rules for this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he that ſeeks all things in ſubordination to his chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt good, hee ſeeks nothing that ſhall fall croſſe unto it: this is the ſigne of a godly man, what ever is croſſe to his chief good, hee counts life not dear for the removall of
<pb facs="tcp:100129:19"/>it, <hi>I count not my life dear unto me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, ſo I may finiſh my courſe with joy, Acts</hi> 20.24 Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eaſe, carnall delight, worldly contentments are not dear unto thee, if God be thy chief good; if thy Eſtate, honour, thy relations, yea, thy life it ſelfe come in competiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between thy God and thee, thou wilt ſay as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr: <hi>ſarwell Wife, farwell Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, farwell Eſtate, yea, farwell life, and give me my Chriſt.</hi> 'Tis with many men as it was with <hi>Demas, Demas</hi> hath forſaken us, and embraced the preſent world, he profeſſes godlineſſe no more; So it is with men, they neglect known duties for temporall advantages; take heed that nothing croſſe thee in thy treaſure, but let all things be ſubordinated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:100129:19"/>
            <p>Then ſecondly, as it muſt not croſſe it, ſo it muſt ſerve it, every thing muſt be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate to his chiefeſt good; thus it was with <hi>Jehu.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 2.9.</note> The Kingdom was in his eye, that was his chiefe good; Now <hi>Jehu's</hi> reformation of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on tended onely to this end, to ſet <hi>Jehu</hi> in his Kingdome; yet hee did the worke that God intended, hee execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Gods judgements up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> hee thought to have had his ends upon God, and God had his ends upon him. But take a godly man whoſe chiefe good is God and godlineſſe, hee loves an Eſtate not for it ſelfe, but that hee might honour God with it: gifts, what doth he value them for? for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification of the body of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100129:20"/>Chriſts wiſdome (ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) is good with an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, <note place="margin">Ecleſ. 7.11.</note> that is when grace teacheth a man to make uſe of it.</p>
            <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">After which his ſoul goes out.</note> Tryall, by which you may find out your treaſure; A mans ſoul goes out towards it with continuall and earneſt breathings, and endleſſe gaſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; ſo you ſhall find it is with naturall men, who have their treaſure in this life, and and whoſe bellies are fed with the providences of God one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and who make a God of their belly, their hearts are only carried out with breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings after this treaſure. But on the other ſide, <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>my ſoul is lifted up to God;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.4.</note> to lift up the ſoule in ſcripture is, to deſire a thing earneſtly. Take a man whoſe treaſure is in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100129:20"/>Heaven, whoſe chief good is God, the continuall gaſpings of his ſoul are after God, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 25.1. he deſires God earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 5.1. <hi>in this wee groane earneſtly,</hi> &amp;c. hee is under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall groanings and gaſp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings after God, though it is true the ſoule finds an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility of enjoying God perfectly in this life; yet you ſhall finde this true, love to him of the right kind is ſo car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried after God, that it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſatisfied, or at reſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out more of the enjoyment of him. Examine therefore your ſoules, what do they moſt breath and pant after conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually, and that's your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">Wherein his ſoule receives ſatiſfaction.</note> That's a mans trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure wherein a mans Soul receives ſatisfaction, and without
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100129:21"/>which hee is never ſatisfied, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 49.18. the worldling <hi>bleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eih his ſoul while he lives;</hi> that's his treaſure; Naturall men are ſatisfied in nothing elſe but in the things of this world, that their ſoules pant and breath after. Take an Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, let every mans purſe be opened, it will not ſatisfie him, he cannot ſit in a low place, becauſe a high place is his chief good; ſo <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> let him have never ſuch honours, hee is not ſatisfied except he be made moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, becauſe his ſoul goes out after high places, hee muſt be had in eſteem of the men of the World. But take a man that hath godlineſs for his chief good, and this he is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in, and nothing elſe, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8. <hi>They ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100129:21"/>ſatisfied with the fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy houſe; and thou ſhalt make them drink of the River of thy pleaſures:</hi> Now give a godly man wealth, it will not ſatisfie him, give him honor, it will not ſatisfie him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.10. a good man ſhall be ſatisfied from himſelf; By theſe rules you may eaſily ſee where your chief good is laid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe</hi> 2. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction.</note> Of Conviction, to ſet forth the miſery of them that miſlay their treaſure, that be deceived in their chiefeſt good. Take heed of laying up your treaſures in this life, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man in this life hath ſome treaſure, or ſome great good; this will ſet forth the miſery and wretched condition of all them that miſplace their treaſure, miſplace their chiefe good. There are many ſorts
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100129:22"/>of men whoſe treaſure is laid up here below, their portion is in this life, they are miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in their chief good, this plainly ſhewes they are in a miſerable condition; and yet this is the condition of moſt of the world, and under which the greateſt part of it will periſh. That I may heighten this Conviction, <note place="margin">Six con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> I ſhall give you ſix conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">The ſcripture ſpeaks of a true treaſure.</note> Conſider, the Scripture ſpeaks of a true treaſure, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.11. <hi>If ye have not been faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the unrighteous Mammon, who will commit to your truſt the true riches:</hi> here's the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he ſets the one againſt the other. There is a true trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and there is a falſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and they that inherit not ſubſtances, inherit ſhadowes.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100129:22"/>
               <hi>Pro.</hi> 23.5 <hi>Wilt thou ſet thine eyes upon that which is not?</hi> they are ſaid not to be, and that upon a twofold account.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe there's no reali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe there's no ſtability in them, that is, in reference to that which you fancy to be in them. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſſe is Idolatry, for it is an Idoll, the Apoſtle ſaith ſo of Riches: 'tis not ſo in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance as it is in appearance; there never was a godly man in the world, whoſe eyes God had opened, but he ſaw that it was onely his thought, his apprehenſion of riches that made them ſeem great. Then they have no ſtability in them: they periſh in the very enjoyment of them; he is a miſerable man that doth not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100129:23"/>Inherit ſuch ſpirituall abiding ſubſtance as God is, and hath his treaſure in God, and the things of God.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">There's a falſe treaſure.</note> There's a falſe treaſure as well as a true: herein lies a great deluſion of ſin and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> to deceive a man in his chief good, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12, 13. <hi>Take heed left there be in any of you an evill heart of unbeliefe in departing from the living God, and left any of you be hardned through the deceitfullnſſe of ſin.</hi> Sathan will labour to deceive you in every thing, but he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours moſtly to deceive you in your chiefeſt good, in drawing you from God; for as the Spirit of God is in directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo the Spirit of <hi>Sathan</hi> is in deluſion. As the ſpirit of God directs a man in this life to carry out affections more
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100129:23"/>to God, and to make his chief good; ſo on the contrary, the Devill doth all to this end, that he may deceive a man of his chiefeſt good, and take off the chiefeſt good, and take off the affections of his heart from God: When <hi>Sathan</hi> fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a mans heart on any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular good, it is to take him off from that that is an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall good: <hi>Sathan</hi> is ſaid to be a murderer from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; how ſo? on this account, becauſe hee deceives perſons of their chiefeſt good, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the life of their ſoules doth lie.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Mans nature abhors to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</note> Conſider the nature of man doth exceedingly abhor to be deceived: the Holy Ghoſt doth charge us that we ſhould not overreach our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the nature of man is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100129:24"/>much inclined to deceive one another, <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.14.</note> and therefore the nature of man doth excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly abhorr to be deceived it ſelf. <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.3.</note> Now there was never ſuch deceit as in the chiefeſt good, to give a man braſſe for gold, and ſtones for bread; To take the Creature for the Creator, to ſet up the Devill in the place of God; This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit is of being cheated in our chief good. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other that are leſſer deceits, he doth deceive in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Acts, as when a man hath been convinced of ſin, pray'd againſt it, and the Devill hath varniſhed it over again, and led him to the Commiſſion of it; but the grand deceit of all is in his chiefeſt good.</p>
            <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil labors above all to deceive you in this.</note> Conſider this is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit that above all, he takes
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100129:24"/>care to hide from you, he will keep you under that all the daies of your life. You have many deceits of Satan laid in a mans way, that may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to him, and theſe a man may recover out of, as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. <hi>That they may reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver themſelves out of the ſnare of the Devill.</hi> He may ſee that in that particular Act he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that which he thought was good, he finds it was not ſo, but he was deceived through the wiles of Satan; a man may ſee the devices of Satan in reference to his dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſinne, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18. But the Devils great deſigne on all unregenerated men, is to keep them in an unregenerate ſtate, more then in unregenerate Acts: Therefore the great work in converſion, is to cauſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100129:25"/>the ſoul to mind its chiefe good; never was there any converted to God and Chriſt, but he ſaw that he erred in his chiefeſt good, and that he had departed from his God; how is a man departed from God? He is departed from God in two things: 1. As his chiefeſt good. 2. As his utmoſt end. How muſt a man returne to God? Firſt, as his chiefeſt good, and then as his utmoſt end.</p>
            <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives moſt, Mat. 7.14.</note> This will be the deceit under which the greateſt part of the world will be damned; for, <hi>ſtraight is the Gate, and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is the way that leadeth to life, and few there be that find it.</hi> All men are carryed forth to ſome good or other, and ſay, <hi>VVho will ſhew us any good?</hi> Pſal. 4. But there are four things that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100129:25"/>moſt of the world do uſually miſtake in.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They take that which is but a ſeeming good, for a reall good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They take that which is a particular good, for an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall good.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They take that which is a temporary good, for aneter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall good.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They take that which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans good, for their own good: Moſt men miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take under theſe four ſorts of good, and ſo periſh.</p>
            <p>6.<note n="6" place="margin">This will cauſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult.</note> If you be deceived in your chiefeſt good, it will be the matter of Satans inſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the matter of your Lamentation for ever. It will be matter of Satans inſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Satan is the envious man: TWO things there are in Satan
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100129:26"/>to ſinners; one is cruell mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings, and the other is cruel mockings of them, as in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 14.11, 12. <hi>How art thou fallen from heaven, O Lucifer Sonne of morning? Nebuchadnezzar</hi> that thought himſelfe as it were placed in heaven, falls downe to hell, he deluded himſelfe. It will be then too late to ſay, <hi>I was ignorant, and as a beaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe men are miſerable, <note place="margin">The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of thoſe that are herein cheated.</note> that are cheated of their chief good, and their miſery lyes in ſix Particulars.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">There's nothing good to ſuch a man.</note> Becauſe there's nothing good to that man that err's in his chiefeſt good, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 5.13. there's a man that made Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches his chiefeſt good; there's no good to him therein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he made not God his chiefeſt good, <hi>his Riches are to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100129:26"/>his hurt:</hi> many a man is made honourable and Rich to his hurt. But are not Ordinances you will ſay, for a mans good? Is it not good to live under the means of grace? to have the droppings of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary? I anſwer no, if not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, the nigher to Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and at diſtance from God, <hi>the nigher to the Curſe,</hi> Heb. 6.7, 8. Ordinances will ripen your ſinnes, and they will haſten your ruine, they will inſnare your ſoules, they will draw out your luſts, and they will ruine you for ever: As every thing is good to a man that is right in his chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt good, ſo nothing is good to that man that errs in his chiefeſt good.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">This will cauſe him to eire in all things.</note> If a man erre in his chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt good, this will make him
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100129:27"/>erre in his judging of al things and perſons in this life; for the rule of every mans judgement is according to his chief good, he errs, and muſt needs do ſo, if he errs in that: Take a man that judgeth finning better then ſuffering, he chuſeth ſin before ſuffering, <hi>Iob</hi> 36.21. <hi>Take heed, regard not iniquity; for this thou haſt choſen rather then affliction:</hi> He chuſeth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent things, before things to come; things that are ſeen, before things that are not ſeen: But to a godly man, ſin is worſe then ſuffering, then death, then hell. It was the ſaying of one of the Martyrs, <hi>He is not praiſe-worthy, nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of praiſe, that God praiſeth not.</hi> A man that hath his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in heaven, he judgeth all things aright according
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100129:27"/>to the heavenly Treaſure.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">This makes him miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place his affections</note> If a man miſtake his chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt good, this cauſeth him to miſplace all the affections of his ſoule; they will be ſet wrong, &amp; are ſet upon wrong objects: The Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks of a <hi>crooked</hi> and a <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Generation,</hi> when they were ſet upon wrong objects, they were in feare where no feare was. Now take an other man whoſe chiefe good is God, he feares sinne, the other feares man; he rejoyces in God, the other rejoyces in man; here the affections of ſoule are miſtaken by miſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the chiefeſt good.</p>
            <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">To loſe his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</note> This makes a man looſe his labour, in what ever he doth all his life time; he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours onely for the meat that periſheth, but not for the meat
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100129:28"/>that endureth for everlaſting life; he ſpends his parts, his ſtrength, and time in vaine: He ſowes the wind, and reaps the whirle winde.</p>
            <p>This grand error makes you erre in every thing you doe; the wicked man is deceived, diſappointed, and at the laſt will be aſhamed of all his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings: But the godly man cannot be deceived, nor diſappointed of his hopes, nor return aſhamed, becauſe he is not miſtaken in his chiefeſt good, and therefore cannot loſe any of his labour.</p>
            <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">This will deſtroy him.</note> This onely will deſtroy the man: This is the grand miſtake; a man may be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in particular things, and yet the ſoule may be ſaved in the day of the Lord: but if once he be deceived in his
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100129:28"/>chiefeſt good, he can never be ſaved: for what is a mans chiefe good here by way of Election, ſhall be hereafter his chiefe good in way of fruition, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 3.11. <hi>For other foundation can no man lay, then that is laid, which is Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi> To erre in this, is a fundamentall er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror; thoſe that erre in matters of practiſe, 'tis ſaid, yet their ſoules might be ſaved, though their labours be loſe; but if thou erreſt in thy chiefe good, thou canſt never be ſaved.</p>
            <p>6.<note n="6" place="margin">Its the greateſt cheat of all.</note> If there were nothing elſe but this, its the greateſt delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and the obſurdeſt cheat in the world, for a man is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and makes that his greateſt happineſſe that is the quite contrary, that will prove his greateſt miſery; bleſſing, or bleſſedneſſe, requires two
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100129:29"/>things. 1. It muſt be that which cannot be loſt. 2. It muſt be that that puts the ſoul into a condition that he he doth not sinne, or that he cannot sinne. He that placeth his happineſſe below God and Heaven, he ſets up an other God, which is the higheſt way of ſinning in the world, and therefore ſee what a miſerable condition that man is in, that ſets his chiefeſt good in things below God and Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vſe.</hi> 3. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vſe</hi> 3. For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Is this a truth that every man in this life hath ſomething hee laies up for his Treaſure, whether it be in Heaven or Earth; then take this exhortation in the words of the text, lay up treaſures in Heaven. Three things I ſhal premiſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some doe obſerve the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100129:29"/>ſweetneſſe of Chriſts Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands how he applies himſelf to the deſires of his people, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt doth not forbid this, hee doth not ſay, let there bee no ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in you; but if you will lay up treaſure, hee tells you where you ſhould lay up the true treaſure. So <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20. he ſends forth the 72 Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and <hi>they rejoyced the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills were ſubject to them;</hi> Now he doth not forbid their joy, but hee doth augment their joy; <hi>Rejoyce rather that your names are written in the book of life:</hi> ſo when he faith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.18. <hi>Feare not him that can kill the body,</hi> he forbids you not altogether to fear, but ſee if your feare be plac'd on the right object, that is, himſelfe more then them: ſo when men
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100129:30"/>are apt to glory in ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency they have obtained, ſaith the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.23. <hi>Let not the wife man glory in his wiſdom, neither let the mighty man glory in his might, let not the rich man glory in his rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, but let him that glorieth, glory in this, that he underſtandeth and knoweth me that I am the Lord.</hi> Set a right object for your glorying in; ſo here hee doth not forbid you to labour for riches, but to be rich towards God; he doth not forbid you to bee adorned, but let it bee with beauties of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's obſerved that there are diverſe waies of treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; <note place="margin">3. Sort of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> there are three forts of treaſures that are laid up, three ſeverall waies.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures on Earth.</note> There are treaſures on
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100129:30"/>Earth, ſome place their hapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on the things below: our Saviour faith, <hi>lock not to the things that are ſeen, but have an eye to the things that are not ſeen.</hi> It was well obſerved by one, that that whieh a man loves and aimes at as his end, that's his treaſure. A man that hath no end beyond this life, hath no treaſure beyond this life, let me be rich, let me be honourable and brave in this world, that's all he looks at. He looks not up to the treaſure above; this man placeth his affections on the Earth, and makes that his portion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There are Treaſures in Hell, <note place="margin">3. Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in Hell.</note> ſome lay up their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in Hell, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.5. <hi>they treaſure up to themſelves wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the day of wrath.</hi> There are two treaſures, one of ſin,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100129:31"/>and the other of wrath, and the one ſits for the other; as the man adds to the one, ſo God adds to the other; for you muſt know as ſinne ripens, ſo doth judgement, as ſin en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth, ſo doth wrath, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.10. <hi>The Rod hath bloſſomed, as Pride hath budded;</hi> It's ſpoken of Gods bringing of wrath upon <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> now mind the gradation, the Rod firſt bloſſoms, then it buds; judgement firſt ripens, and then ruins; you read in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of an Ephah of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, that is, that which notes the full meaſure of wickedneſſe; and you read of a Talent, which is judgement proportioned to the ſin. As you fill up the treaſures of your ſins. ſo God fills up the treaſures of his wrath: you
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100129:31"/>think you onely carry on your own treaſure, but God is car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on his treaſury of wrath alſo. The</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">2 Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in Heaven.</note> Sort are thoſe that lay up treaſure in Heaven, that place their happineſſe in the chief good, in nothing but Heaven, that have aimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond this life, the things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent are but for their way, not for the end of their Journey. Every man is as his chiefe good, and as his utmoſt end is; if thy end be Earthly, thou art a man of the Earth; if Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, thou art a man of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. It is ſaid, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17.14. <hi>Men of the world that have their portion in this life:</hi> They are called men of this world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their end and aime is not beyond this world. But the Saints and Citizens of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:100129:32"/>Heaven are ſo called, becauſe their end and aime is beyond this life, and their chief good lies there.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You are to obſerve the manner and nature of this command; lay up treaſures in Heaven, his meaning is not, that they ſhould lay up no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on Earth: To lay up on Earth is a duty, as to provide things neceſſary for the body; but in eſpeciall manner bee ſure to lay up in Heaven, have your hearts in Heaven, though your bodies be on the Earth, we ought to lay up ſomething in ſummer againſt the time of Winter; Parents ought to lay up for their Children. Lay not up treaſure on Earth; that is to ſay, as it is contrary to a treaſure in Heaven, but ſo as it may be helpfull to thy trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100129:32"/>in Heaven. Again, lay not up treaſure on earth, ſo, as if there were an abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of it, or as if a man could not live without it, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke</hi> 12.15. a mans life conſiſteth not in the abundance of the things that he poſſeſſeth. Laſtly, lay not up treaſure on Earth, ſo as to neglect Heaven, let not this be a means to take off your hearts from higher things, if ſo, your treaſure will be your curſe, and God gives you a great eſtate in great Judgement.</p>
            <p>Let us now come to ſet home this Exhortation, ſeeing ſome lay up treaſures in Earth, ſome lay up treaſures in Heaven, do you be exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to lay up your treaſures in Heaven.</p>
            <p>Four things I will ſpeak to in proſcuting of it.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:100129:33"/>
            <p n="1">1. What is meant by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven?</p>
            <p n="2">2. What are the treaſures of Heaven.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What is it to lay up trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in Heaven.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Some arguments to enforce the Exhortation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, what is meant by Heaven? <note place="margin">What is meant by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> There is a twofold Expoſition of it, and we may make an improvement of both of them.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">God himſelf.</note> By Heaven, ſome expound it of God himſelfe, as if hee ſhould ſay, lay up your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in God, with God: ſo that they take Heaven for God, that is the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the pleaſures of Heaven. Now this will help you to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand other Scriptures, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.25. <hi>The Baptiſm of</hi> John, <hi>was it from Heaven?</hi> that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:100129:33"/>is, from the God of Heaven; Heaven is there put for God: ſo <hi>Luke</hi> 15.18. <hi>Father I have ſinned against Heaven;</hi> that is, againſt the God of Heaven, the God that dwells in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, there's your happineſſe alone, let your chief good be laid up in him, let him who hath promiſed to be our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and exceeding great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward be our treaſure in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; yet you are to conſider that the Scripture ſpeakes of other treaſures in Heaven, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.33. <hi>Provide your ſelves a treaſure in Heaven that faileth not;</hi> that is, of good works, but they are onely as they aim at God; God is himſelf the great reward, and the rich treaſure of Heaven; this is the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of every gratious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of duty, 'tis a
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:100129:34"/>treaſure of heaven, becauſe it is recorded in heaven by God himſelfe, lay up therefore your treaſures with God, that he may be your eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. The</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">The third Heaven.</note> Expoſition of this place, is this; They take Heaven for the third Heaven, the higheſt Heaven, the habitation of Gods majeſtie and glory, the place where the Saints ſhall be with God, where the Angels have Communion with God, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23.23. He is ſaid, <hi>to fill heaven and earth;</hi> 'tis called the place where his honour dwels; there you have two things. 1. The Viſion of him. 2. The Fruition of him, ſo 'tis ſaid to be a City, <note place="margin">Heb. 11.10.</note> whoſe <hi>builder and maker is God;</hi> this being the place of the Saints, therefore they are exhorted to lay up
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:100129:34"/>their treaſure in it: the time will ſhortly come, when the Saints ſhall be removed from earth to heaven, for here they have no abiding City: now their happineſſe in heaven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to enjoy God to eternity, for this cauſe they are exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to lay up a Treaſure in heaven. Well, take it in both theſe ſences, in God, or in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, where the eternall enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God ſhall be.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond place; What is that Treaſure that a man ſhould lay up in heaven? We ſhall underſtand it by the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite; there is a treaſure that man layes up on earth as his chief good, as Riches, Honor, High-places, Pleaſure, popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar applauſe, &amp;c. and where his Treaſure is, there his heart is: So there is a treaſure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:100129:35"/>which is a mans chiefe good; it is God that is his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Chriſt as Mediator that brings him to God.</p>
            <p>There are three things that demonſtrate, <note place="margin">Nothing but God can be a mans treaſure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> that none but God can be a mans treaſure in heaven.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Becauſe a man muſt love it beſt.</note> A Mans treaſure is that which he loves beſt, and a man muſt love nothing more then God; nay a mans chiefe good is that which he loves with an infinite love, that he doth never ſay I have enough. The <hi>Hebrew</hi> word for Treaſures, ſignifies that which a man ſets his heart moſt on; where a mans love goes, there a mans zeal goes, that's his treaſure that carryes out his love.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Prize it moſt.</note> That which a man pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeth moſt, which a man ſets higheſt price on, that's a mans
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:100129:35"/>Treaſure; now a man ſhould prize nothing more then God; Kingdomes and Nations be not deare to God for the ſake of the Saints, therefore King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Nations ſhould not be deare to the Saints in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of God, they ſhould prize nothing in compariſon of him, much leſſe in compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with him.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Relieup on it.</note> Upon a mans Treaſure he relies for ſupplies, that which a man makes his Treaſure in Calamities and Diſtreſſes he goes to it; therefore <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.25. <hi>Whom have I in heaven but thee? and there's none upon earth that I deſire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thee: my fleſh and my heart faileth; but God is the ſtrength of my heart, and my portion for ever.</hi> Thus you ſee every man muſt be ſupplyed out of his owne Treaſure.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:100129:36"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdy,</hi> You will ſay, God is in heaven above, the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his holineſſe and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; How can we be ſaid to lay up God for a Treaſure? 'Tis true, God is in heaven, he made the heavens, and he dwels in heaven; but he is not laid up there for thy trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, unleſſe thou cloſeſt with him by faith, and lay him up for thy God, and in ſo doing he will be thy treaſure; for though he dwels in heaven, yet he dwels alſo in <hi>humble and contrite Spirits.</hi> Now there are ſix Rules to get the God of heaven to be our God and Treaſure.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Chuſe God ſo thy trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> He that will lay up Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in heaven, he muſt chuſe God for his treaſure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, not onely the joyes and delights of heaven, the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:100129:36"/>of heaven, but the God of heaven, that which thou chuſeſt is thy treaſure: If a man chuſe Honour, and Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and Pleaſure, that is his treaſure; what you chuſe firſt, you prize moſt, and you ſhall be ſure to have God for your treaſure if you chuſe him.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Part with all for him.</note> Then part with all other treaſures for him: No man can have two Treaſures, no more then he can have two Maſters, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21. Look to your ſelves, you have not God for your treaſure, except you part with all other treaſures for him.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Let thy heart be after him.</note> The ſoul is to be carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out after this treaſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly; that man that layes up God for his treaſure, his heart is continually carryed after him, and ſo muſt yours,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:100129:37"/>if you will have God to be your Treaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.24. How doth the foul go out af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God? <note place="margin">Pſa. 119.20.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoul pants for the longings it hath towards thee; my ſoul longeth, yea even fainteth for the Lord.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.2.</note> ſo ſaith <hi>David:</hi> If your ſouls do not go out after God, and reliſh the ſweetneſſe of God, certainly you have no part nor portion in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">Live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him.</note> If you would have God for your treaſure, live upon him; men live upon their treaſures, ſo muſt you upon your God.</p>
            <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">Glory in him.</note> Would you have the God of heaven for your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, then glory in him; what a man labours to get for his treaſure, that he glories in. Every man values other men as he values his treaſure; take
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:100129:37"/>a man that makes Riches his treaſure, let the perſon be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo honourable he deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, becauſe he hath not ſo great an eſtate as he: ſo a godly man values every man according as his chiefeſt good is, he is worth no more then he is worth in Gods account, therefore he eſteems no more of him.</p>
            <p>6.<note n="6" place="margin">Add to thy trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> What ever is your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, if you lay up your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in any thing, you muſt uſe all means to add unto it, and make a daily increaſe, the increaſe of your treaſure coms in by adding to it, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 33.6. Why doth <hi>Hezekiab</hi> lay up treaſure in God? he gets a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intereſt in God, therefore the man is bleſs'd with his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: wiſdom and knowledge ſhall be the ſtability of thy
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:100129:38"/>
               <hi>times, and thought of Salvation, and this is, becauſe the fear of the Lord is his treaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth particular is to give you ſome grounds to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the Exhortation; is there a treaſure in Heaven? then do not be ſuch Enemies to your ſoules as not to lay up trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures there. There are four Arguments to enforce the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">No trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low God, will be laſting.</note> No treaſure below God will be laſting, Chriſt ſpeakes therefore to you continually to lay up your treaſure in Heaven, becauſe there will come a time when all trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures laid up below God, will be expunged and gone, and then what will you live upon? 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29.31. the Apoſtle faith, <hi>the time is ſhort, and the faſhion of this world
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:100129:38"/>paſſeth away;</hi> 'tis a Metaphor ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from things folded up, a great part of time is unfold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and unwoven, it's almoſt ſpent, there's abundance of life run out already, and little left behind; there is an eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that will never be ſpent af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all thy time here is ſpent, lay up therefore treaſures there.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Nor hopes of Heaven without this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> Heaven is the place to which you hope to go, now carry your treaſures with you, and ſend your treaſures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, or elſe there can be no hopes of entering into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. This is the Exhortation of our Saviour, when he faith, <hi>lay up Treaſures in Heaven;</hi> hee ſeems to ſpeak to the hopes of perſons going to Heaven, goe powre out your ſoules before the Lord, make ſure of your
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:100129:39"/>Heavenly manſion; you will leave the eſtates and your fine houſes behind you, poure out your ſoules to the Lord, make ſure of your intereſt in Chriſt, that you may carry your treaſure with you.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">God is an all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient treaſure.</note> Conſider, God is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and true treaſurer, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lay up your treaſure in Heaven: God is ſelf-ſufficient to himſelf, and he is allſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to you; But if thy treaſure be here below on this ſide to God, it will not laſt, that which is thy treaſure in this life, will be thy Torment in the life to come <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.3. <hi>your Gold and Silver is cankred, and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſſe against you, and ſhall eat your bread as it were fire: yee have heaped treaſure together for the laſt daies:</hi> when judgement
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:100129:39"/>ſhall come, your Torment ſhall then begin, and you ſhall have the greateſt plagues at the laſt day of judgement; your treaſures will then cruſh and begin to be your tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that which now thou chooſeſt to be thy trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, will then be thy tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentor. The onely way to preſerve what you have of this treaſure on Earth, is to lay up treaſures in Heaven. In the houſes of godly men are the beſt and pretiouſeſt treaſures, becauſe they come into them from a promiſe, and ſo they have much ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in them. All the cares of wicked men is what they ſhall have, but a godly man, that hath Communion with God, and an intereſt in Heaven; theſe men look upon it as a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:100129:40"/>priviledge what they ſhould do for God.</p>
            <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">If God be not your treaſure here hee will not herafter.</note> Argument; you that have not God for your treaſure here, you ſhall never have him for your treaſure hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for after this life a man can never change his chiefe good, that which is ſo here, ſhall be ſo hereafter; therefore if you have not a treaſure laid up in God in this life, he will not be thy God in glory here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and yet God ſhall be all in all.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen already the miſery of thoſe that erre in their chiefect good: Now I ſhall come to ſhew you the happy condition of them that have pitched upon their chief good, and that have laid up their treaſures in Heaven. Whatſoever they are in this
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:100129:40"/>world; yet in regard of their chief good they have not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carried. <note place="margin">A good man is every way bleſſed.</note> O how bleſſed is that ſoul that hath not miſplaced his treaſure. A godly man is every way a bleſſed man.</p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">In the pardon of his ſin.</note> Hee is bleſſed in regard of the pardon of his ſin; <hi>bleſſed is the man whoſe tranſgreſſion is forgiven, and whoſe ſin is covered,</hi> Pſ. 32.1.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his ſoul.</note> Hee is bleſſed in regard of the diſpoſition of his ſoul; <hi>bleſſed are the pure in heart, for they ſhall ſee God.</hi> Mat. 5.8.</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">In hunger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings after ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> He is bleſſed in his hung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and thirſtings after or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances; <hi>Bleſſed are they that dwell in thy houſe, for they will be ſtill praiſing thee,</hi> Pſal. 84.4.</p>
            <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">In his acting to God.</note> Hee is bleſſed in his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiall actings to God; <hi>bleſſed
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:100129:41"/>are the undefiled in the way that walk in the Law of the Lord:</hi> Pſal. 119.1.</p>
            <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">In his expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Hee is bleſſed in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.18. <hi>Bleſſed are they that wait for him.</hi> Nay, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his very Afflictions are bleſſed; <hi>Pſal</hi> 94.10. bleſſed is the man whom thou chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt and teacheſt out of thy Law; Thus you ſee every way how a ſoule that hath made God his treaſure is bleſſed. But wherein lies the top of his bleſſedneſſe, <note place="margin">But the top of his bleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe is in his chiefe good.</note> and the height of his happineſſe? he is bleſſed in his chief good, and there lies the height of his bleſſedneſſe, unto which, and in compariſon of which all theſe are but ſubordinate and inferiour bleſſedneſſes. Look to the Angells in the glory of of heaven, they are bleſſed.</p>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:100129:41"/>
            <p>Firſt, in their in ward quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications and endowments; their wiſdome, their power, their zeal, they are bleſſed in every reſpect.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in regard of their offices and imployments, they are principalities and powers, they are Co-workers with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they are bleſſed for their Activities in thoſe offices, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.14. <hi>They go and return like lightning:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Wherein the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs lies.</note> but where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in lies the top of the Angells bleſſedneſſe in heaven? it lies in this, that they have pitch'd aright upon the chiefeſt good, they have not erred in their treaſure; nay, wherein lies the bleſſedneſſe of Chriſt himſelf as Mediator? hee was every way bleſſed, hee was the heire of all things, and appointed
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:100129:42"/>unto glory, and to a glory ſuitable to the ſervice that he did perform, which neither men nor Angells were able to doe; But wherein lies the top of Chriſts glory and bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.5. you ſhall ſee where it lies; <hi>the Lord is the portion of mine inheritance;</hi> his bleſſedneſſe lay in the chief good. The ſame is true of the glorified Saints in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the ſoules of juſt men made perfect, the glory of the Elect, and the top of all their bleſſedneſſe is that they have pitched upon the right good. On the contrary, what's the miſery of the damned in hell? <note place="margin">Wherein the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the damned lies.</note> there is nothing wanting to make them miſerable, as there is nothing wanting to make the other bleſſed. If you look upon their ſins, you muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:100129:42"/>in hell, ſin is their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: If you conſider the bottomleſſe pit, the burning lake in which they are ſhut up, the worm of conſcience that is ever gnawing and wounding of them, for ſo it is in all thoſe damned ſpirits in hell, this muſt needs make their miſery very miſerable: but wherein lies the top of their miſery? alas it lies in none of theſe, it is in this, that they have erred in their chiefeſt good. An antient writer <hi>(Chryſoſtome)</hi> ſaith, put a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of them together in hell, and here is the worſt of their Torment, their erring in their chief good: ſo then there is none miſerable like thoſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that have erred in their chief good, nor none bleſſed like theſe Saints that have
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:100129:43"/>pitched upon their chiefe good. The miſery of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned lies in two things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe they have forſaken God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe God hath forſaken them; they have ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Lord, and the Lord hates them, herein now doth lie the top of their miſery, as this was the top of their folly, and the top of their vanity to neglect the chief good.</p>
            <p>Now there are variety of comforts belonging to the Saints of God; But there are ſome great grounds of comfort that belong to thoſe that have choſe God for their chiefeſt good; and from theſe grounds ſhould our comfort flow: As there are ſome grand promiſes that are recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in Scripture, which doe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:100129:43"/>wrap up all the reſt of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in them, <note place="margin">The three great ptomiſes</note> and they are three.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I will give you my Son.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I will give you my ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I will give you my ſelf: A godly man ſhould take comfort from all the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, but eſpecially from the great promiſes: for if a man be much in the leaſt duties of Religion, and neglect the greateſt, hee gives juſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſuſpect the truth of his obedience; and ſo if a man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the leſſer promiſes, and look not to the greater, hee gives juſt cauſe to ſuſpect the truth of his comfort: why is a godly man ſo happy a man? It is in this, that he hath not erred in his chief good. But
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:100129:44"/>there are ſeven grounds of the greateſt comfort that I know in all the book of God, <note place="margin">Seven grounds of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for thoſe that have choſen God for their treaſure.</note> ariſing from this conſideration, <hi>I have not miſplaced my treaſure, I have not erred in my chiefe good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Hereby thou maiſt ſee the riches of Gods love un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee.</note> Hereby the ſoul may ſee the riches as well as the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the love of God, I have not miſcarried in that which is the greateſt error of the world, I have not gone with thoſe who have their portion in this life: now its a great mercy to bee delivered from thoſe sinns of laying up your treaſure in this life; then this is much more a greater mercy, that a man hath not miſpla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his chiefeſt good, for miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placing a mans chiefeſt good, 'tis the greateſt sinne, and the greateſt judgement that can befall him. The Scripture
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:100129:44"/>ſpeaks of delivering ſoules up to the Devill; <note place="margin">Satan is both Lord &amp; Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner.</note> and there is a twofold delivering ſoules up to the Devill.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As a Lord.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As an Executioner.</p>
            <p>Firſt to deliver up a man to <hi>Sathan</hi> as a Lord, ſo <hi>Judas</hi> was; the Lord Chriſt delivered him to <hi>Satan</hi> as a Lord to rule over him.</p>
            <p>But, Secondly, when the Lord ſhall give a man over to <hi>Sathan</hi> as an Executioner, that <hi>Sathan</hi> ſhall terrifie his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: now for a godly man to be able to look into his owne condition and ſay, when I looked abroad into the world, I ſee one man place his chiefe good in riches, another in honours another in pleaſure; but in the midſt of all theſe though I have miſcarried in
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:100129:45"/>many things, yet here is my comfort I have not miſcarried in my chiefeſt good. There is not any thing will comfort a godly man more then this, when hee comes to look the King of terrors in the face, nothing will be ſuch pleaſure to his ſoul as this: when <hi>Sathan</hi> ſhall triumph over moſt of the wordl, the poor ſoul ſhall bee able to triumph over all the powers of darkneſſe; I am poor, I am ignorant, I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy; but through grace I obtained that mercy not to be cheated of my chiefeſt good: here will lie a mans wiſdom, and here will be a mans glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; it's a mans chief good that will be a mans wiſdome or folly for ever hereafter. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.42. <hi>Mary hath choſen the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part whieh ſhall not be taken
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:100129:45"/>way from her:</hi> wee read it the good part; and herein lay her wiſdome, and herein lies the wiſdome of all men in their Election, in a mans Election his wiſdome lies, and above all choices he make choice of his chiefeſt good: I have been a fool in many things, but bleſſed be the name of God, I have been wiſe in this thing; I have been deceived in many things, but I have not erred in this: If this doth not ſtand by a godly man in the greateſt troubles, there is nothing that can or will do it.</p>
            <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">The true chiefe good ſhal neverb; taken from thee.</note> Comfort is this, I have choſen the true chiefe good that ſhall never be taken from me, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.42, <hi>Which ſhall not be taken away from her.</hi> There is no man miſcarries in his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but he that layes it up
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:100129:46"/>below, and there is no treaſure a man layes up below, but he ſhal be taken from it, &amp; it ſhall be taken from him. Now one of the Ancients obſerve, that earthly treaſure is loſt, either from cauſes within, or from cauſes without: From cauſes within, Riches have principles of decayes in themſelves, there is a Moth that comes out of your fineſt Garments, and there will come droſſe out of your pureſt Gold; for all the Creatures came under the Covenant of God at firſt, and that Covenant being broken, thoſe Creatures come under the curſe of God. Then from principles without, Theeves will ſteale them: man falls from God, and all things elſe fall from him, and this is the great ground from whence all the periſhing nature of a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:100129:46"/>mans treaſure comes that is laid below: But here lyes the difference between the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures below, and the Treaſures above. <hi>Auſtin</hi> hath an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſaying, That a mans chief good is given to no man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will, nor taken from no man againſt his will, but the good here below is. The good above is lyable to no vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence without, nor no decay within; no oppoſition then can hinder comfort from the perſons of thoſe whoſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is above. If Riches be a mans chiefe good, it ſhall be taken from him; but thy chief good eannot be taken from thee, and oh what a ground of comfort is this to to graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſoules!</p>
            <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Thou ſhalt be guided in thy way, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced when wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> Comfort; A man that hath choſen the true chiefe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:100129:47"/>good, he hath alwaies ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to guid his way, he hath alwaies ſomething to reduce his wanderings: 1. From this chiefe good he hath the guide of his way; this is to the ſoul as the Center is to the ſtone, the ſtone moves towards the Center, and moves towards it the right way; what guids the motion to the Center, but the Center? ſo a godly man, if he want a particular Rule, yet this generall Rule, God is his Center, is that that leads him to move towards him, that guids him in the right way. Whats the great conſultation of the ſoul? It is this, O what will bring me neereſt to my chiefeſt good? and 'tis the chiefe good that is the guide of all our motions, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.22. <hi>If thine eye be ſingle, thy whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:100129:47"/>is full of light: Auſtin</hi> ſaith, Its the intention of the man that is the eye of the man, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle intentions is his ſingle eye, and a ſingle eye, is an eye that looks purely upon God. As the intention of the eye guids the man, ſo the intention of the ſoule guides the way what carryes me moſt to my chiefe good this is that that guids the way. 2. This haſh a great influence alſo to reduce mens wanderings; many that have choſen God for their chiefeſt good, do many times depart from him; now what ſhall bring him back againe? it is the eying of the chiefe good, this brings the man again: we have all gone aſtray like a ſheep, but now we are return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſhepheard of our ſoules; There is not any thing
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:100129:48"/>can reduce a man to God, that hath departed from God, but the placing his chiefe good in him: that ſoul, whoſe chiefe good is at home, will not long ſtay abroad.</p>
            <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">Unto thy chiefe good thou maiſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire and fetch comfort.</note> Unto a mans chiefe good his ſoul retires, and from it he fetcheth chief comfort up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, and ſo may Saints: he that makes choice of the chiefeſt good, can ſay, I am ſure of this Comfort, <hi>The Name of my God is a ſtrong Tower, Prov.</hi> 18.11. therefore I will runne to it and be ſafe; the Rich man goes to his wealth, the righteous man goes to his God. A godly man is able to ſay in thoſe diſtreſſe, though I have no Riches to comfort me, and very few friends to ſtand by me; yet I have a God, a Chriſt, a Heaven, a new Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:100129:48"/>a new image which I can retreat to, and rely upon in all occaſions; and thus the ſoule can triumph in his chief good over the chiefeſt evills; as the Spouſe (it is a voyce of triumph) <hi>my beloved is the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of ten thouſand, Cant.</hi> 5.10. There is all a mans comfort in that which is his treaſure, now God being his Treaſure, there is his comfort; and hence it is, that theſe dare compare with any perſons in any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.8. compared with <hi>verſe</hi> 22. in <hi>verſe</hi> 8. <hi>In God we make our boaſt all the day long,</hi> and <hi>verſe</hi> 22. <hi>For thy ſake we are killed all the day long:</hi> What? boaſt of God, and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all the day long for God? I, here is the comfort of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, he can retire unto his chiefe good, and whenſoever
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:100129:49"/>he retreats to it, he is filled full of comfort by it.</p>
            <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">This may be a comfort in all thy failings. Prov. 20.9.</note> 'Tis of great Comfort to a godly man in the middeſt of all his failings, yet I have not failed in chuſing God for my chiefeſt good. The beſt men may, nay muſt ſay, Who can make his heart clean? and when he looks back upon his way, he muſt ſay, My heart bath runne out inordinately after this thing and that thing, and I have neglected my chief good and my treaſure, but for this, I deſire to be aſhamed all my life, but my happineſſe is laid up in him and no other, I have choſen him for my chief good, and though I have fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in many things, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.2. <hi>Yet I have not wickedly departed from my God:</hi> departed he hath, and many times departed wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:100129:49"/>and willingly; but wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly I have not departed from God. What is it for a man to depart from God willingly? 'Tis for a man to place his chief good ſome where elſe then in God, to go out after an other God: now in this <hi>David</hi> can rejoyce in the midd'ſt of his failings, and ſo maiſt thou. In that he hath not ſo departed from one God to ſet up ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: therefore this, and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, can comfort the Saints in the midd'ſt of all their fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: The departings from God, is the greateſt trouble that doth befall them; but yet here is their great comfort that they have not left him as their Treaſure, though they may ſometimes leave him as their Lord.</p>
            <p>6.<note n="6" place="margin">That which thou lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt up for thy chief good herethou ſhalt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</note> Comfort which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:100129:50"/>that which thou haſt laid up for thy chief good here by Election, that thou ſhalt enjoy in the world to come by fruition, therefore <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, A mans bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is begun in Election here, but finiſhed and perfected in fruition hereafter, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.2. ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will be thy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great reward:</hi> doſt thou chuſe God for thy chiefeſt good here? if thou doſt, that which thou chuſeſt in one world, thou ſhalt enjoy in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
            <p>7.<note n="7" place="margin">Thou ſhalt be bleſſed with the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God.</note> He that hath laid up his chiefe good in heaven, ſhall be happy with the ſame hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe that God himſelfe is happy withall; look wherein Gods bleſſedneſſe lyes, in that ſhall thy bleſſedneſſe lie: wherein doth Gods bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:100129:50"/>lie? it lyes in himſelf, his chiefe good lies in himſelfe, for the Creature to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge God for his chiefe good ſo farre as the Creature is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, he is bleſſed with the bleſſedneſſe of God himſelfe, and thou doſt enter into the joy of thy Lord.</p>
            <p>Now I proceed to the latter part of the Text, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:100129:51"/>
               <head>For where the Treaſure is, there will the heart be alſo.</head>
               <p>Out of which words, I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this obſervation, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That a mans chiefe good is At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive of the heart; <note place="margin">Doct.</note> or the Treaſure where ever it is, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes the heart with it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where ever a mans Treaſure is, there will his heart be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>THere are four things I ſhall ſpeak to by way of Explication.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To ſhew you what is meant by the heart: By heart in in Scripture, is meant the whole ſoul.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:100129:51"/>
               <p n="2">2. That the ſoul of man, the heart goes out of it ſelfe for its happineſſe, for its chiefe good; or thus, the chiefe good of man is without himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. 'Tis a matter of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, where a mans heart is placed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the heart doth alwaies follow the Treaſure, the heart and the Treaſure will be together, and none can put them aſunder.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We ſhall give you the grounds of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> What is meant by the heart? <note place="margin">By the heart is meant. 1. The whole ſoule.</note> By the heart in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is meant the whole ſoul. The <hi>Hebrews,</hi> generally place the Government of man in the heart, and make the heart the ſeat of the reaſonable ſoul; ſo that you ſhall find the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:100129:52"/>commonly ſpeaking of it: Firſt, if you look to the whole ſoule as corrupt, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanctified, ſo corruption goes through all the faculties of the ſoule, but the heart is ſaid to be the ſeat thereof, <hi>ler.</hi> 17.9. <hi>The heart is deceitfull above all things, and deſperately nicked:</hi> and 1 Pet. 3.4. 'tis called, <hi>The hidden man of the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. If you looke upon the ſoule as renewed, 'tis ſaid, <hi>With the heartman believes,</hi> Rom. 10.10. But the heart of man in Scripture, is ſometimes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for thoſe things that are ſcituated, and have their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation eſpecially in the heart. As wiſdome is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the heart, or folly, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim is a ſilly Dove without a heart,</hi> Hoſ. 7.11. and <hi>he that truſts to his own heart is a foole,</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:100129:52"/>Prov. 28.26. that is, hee that leanes to his owne wiſdome: Again, <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> the heart is put for Conſcience, <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſmote him when he cut off the lap of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment. There's a conviction of the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that's called the heart: ſomtimes for the memory, which is the treaſurie of the ſoul. But there are three things meant by the heart in this place.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">3. The thoughts and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> The thoughts, Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and conſultations of the heart, where the treaſure is, there is the heart; that is, there is the thoughts, there is the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and conſultations of the heart, in theſe all the thoughts and contrivances of the ſoule are, now where a man's treaſure is, there are
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:100129:53"/>theſe, 2 <hi>Kings.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Did not my heart go along with thee.</hi> How did the Prophets heart goe with him? his thoughts went with him. So <hi>Iob</hi> 17.11. the <hi>thoughts</hi> of the <hi>heart</hi> are there called the heart, in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew it is the <hi>poſſeſſions of the heart,</hi> for as what ever you do poſſeſſe in the body, the body can ſee a glory, and caſt a ſweetneſſe in all things here below, ſo the ſoul can taſt a a ſweetneſſe, and ſee a glory in all things above.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">4. Love &amp; affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> By heart is meant a mans love, and affection, his deſires and longings for, in theſe the ſoule goes out towards its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.8. As it is ſaid of <hi>Shechem,</hi> his houſe clave to <hi>Dinah.</hi> Now where your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, ther's your love, there your deſires are, the longings
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:100129:53"/>of your Soules are after it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">5. Ioy and delight.</note> By the heart is meant a man's delight, the joy of his heart, that whereby the great Comfort of his life comes in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.16. <hi>If riches increaſe, ſet not your heart on him;</hi> that is, do not place the comfort of your lives in them, let not your hearts be ſwallowed up by them: Now where a man's treaſure is, there his thoughts are, there his love is, there the joy and delight of his ſoul is. The</p>
               <p>Second Propoſition is this, <note place="margin">Mans chief is without himſelf.</note> that the ſoul of man goes out of it ſelf for happineſſe, for its treaſure is without it ſelf, It's Gods honour, his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative onely to have his bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe to be himſelf, hee is unto himſelfe the chief good,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:100129:54"/>he hath nothing without him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to augment his happineſs. <note place="margin">Gods bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> The Lord Jeſus Chriſt as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator in all his obedience, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded nothing to the bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God; <hi>My goodneſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to thee.</hi> Pſal. 16.2. But this is Gods Prerogative one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have his happineſſe in himſelf; as for creatures that are capable of a chiefe good, their happineſſe is not in themſelves, but in their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which is good, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their heart is to go out af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their treaſure. And here take notice of two great depths in Divinity.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Depth.</note> Man hath not the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt good in himſelf, his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe comes not from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and hence it is that in reference to all things, hee is a dependant Creature. And
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:100129:54"/>therefore the ſoul is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally reſtleſſe, becauſe it ſeeks to joyne it ſelfe to its chiefeſt good, which is without it ſelf: you have a ſaying, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.14. <hi>a good man ſhall be ſatisfied from himſelf;</hi> It is not from himſelf as ſeparated from God, but from himſelf is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God wherein his bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe lies: not ſelfe in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to God, but ſelf in-ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination to God, and ſo a man is ſatisfied from himſelf; that is; hee goes not out of himſelfe when hee goes into God, becauſe he is made one with God.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Depth.</note> Depth in Divinity is this; that it is the nature and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the reaſonable ſoul to make out to a chiefe good without it ſelfe; this is the nature of it in its Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:100129:55"/>it doth not onely ſeek its own preſervation, but it ſeeks its owne perfection. This is that which is the working of every Greature, much more of the reaſonable Greature, becauſe it hath not a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain at home, it muſt go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to draw; and becauſe it hath not food at home, it muſt go out to gather; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth obſerve very wel, that man is a midle Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wel, there is ſome thing above him, and ſome thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him: That ſoul that hath its chief good below it ſelfe, is a miſerable ſoul; That ſoul that hath its chief good above it ſelf, <note place="margin">The good of the ſoul is above it ſelf.</note> is a happy ſoul; here is the happineſſe of the Saints, that their happineſſe is above themſelves ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.27. <hi>Labour not for the meate
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:100129:55"/>which periſheth, but for the meate which endureth unto everlaſting life, which the Son of man ſhall give unto you:</hi> the ſoul goes out to eat and to drink; Now the ſoule that feeds upon ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing below it ſelf is miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but that ſoul that feeds on ſomthing above it ſelf, is bleſſed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.20. the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaks of ſome that <hi>feed upon aſhes, a deceived heart hath turned them aſide, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay, is there not a lie in my right hand?</hi> And thus doth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man feed whoſe chief food is below himſelf, he feeds on Aſhes, not on ſpirituall food, he feeds of the Earth as hee lives in the Earth. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.10 <hi>If Riches encreaſe, ſet not your heart upon them,</hi> hee ſets his heart on Riches, and therefore his heart cannot be ſet on
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:100129:56"/>God, and his heart is ſet ſo upon riches as to ſuck ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from them for his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and for his perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo a godly mans heart is ſet upon God, doth ſuck out of the ſweetneſſe of God for his preſervation, and for his perfection, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.11. <hi>They ſhall ſuck and be ſatisfied with the breaſts of his Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now give me leave to ſhew you the miſery of them that ſet their happineſſe in things below themſelves; here's their miſery in three things. <note place="margin">The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of thoſe that ſet their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in things below them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. You draw where there is no water, the Creature is but vanity, all things below are ſo; you ſuck where there is no milk, all theſe things are emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that you think to find a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in.</p>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:100129:56"/>
               <p n="2">2. The more your ſouls go out to theſe things for their Treaſure, the more the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite is increaſed, but the leſſe 'tis ſatisfied; for I told you, that all the Creatures, the more a man hath to doe with them, the more his appetite is to them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider what is there to be had in theſe Creature-comforts, when your ſouls goe forth after them, what do you leave for them? <hi>You have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me the fountain of living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and have hewen to your ſelves Ciſterns, broken Ciſterns that will hold no water,</hi> Jer. 2.13. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve foure Particulars from hence.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All the good you have in a Creature, <note place="margin">Creature comforts compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a Ciſtern.</note> is but a Ciſtern, they have no good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, no more then is put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:100129:57"/>
               <p n="2">2. A Ciſtern is but of a ſmall compaſſe, it will hold but a little, a man can ſee an end of its perfection, but of a Fountain thou canſt ſee no end thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Its water that will die and periſh, therefore oppoſed to living water, it will be a withering comfort.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They will all leak out of the bottom, therefore they are ſaid to be <hi>broken Ciſterns.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what is the water of the Fountaine? what is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that is in God? There five things in it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">The comforts of God compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a fountain</note> The water in the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine is originally in it ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Its there continually.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Its is there inexhauſtibly.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is there communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, the Fountaine natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſends forth ſtreames.</p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:100129:57"/>
               <p n="5">5. The comfort that is in God, is living comfort, the water that goes forth is living water.</p>
               <p>Third General Propoſition; <note place="margin">Its a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment where our hearts are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cad.</note> That it is matter of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment in Chriſt's acount, and it ſhould be ſo in ours al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, where our hearts are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Let me open this; The Lord hath in Scripture given eſpecial directions for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a mans heart, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Conſider your waies,</hi> in the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> it is, <hi>Set your heart upon your waies;</hi> ſo <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.46. <hi>Set your hearts unto all the words which I teſtifie among you this day.</hi> Now that it is a matter of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence where the heart is ſet, there are theſe grounds for it.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">God mainly looks at the heart,</note> Its the heart mainely that God looks upon and doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:100129:58"/>he looks not upon what man looks upon, man looks upon the outſide, but God looks upon the inſide, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.9. <hi>For the eyes of the Lord run to and fro throughout the whole earth, to ſhew himſelfe ſtrong in the behalſe of them whoſe heart is perfect towards him;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe God looks upon the heart, it is matter of great conſequence where we place our hearts.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">God claimes the heart.</note> Its the heart mainly that God laies claime unto, and that he calls for, <hi>My Sonne, give me thy heart, Prov.</hi> 23.26.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">The man is where the heart is.</note> Its matter of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, becauſe where the heart is, there's the man; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where the ſoule is gone, the man is gone, where the heart goes, the man follows.</p>
               <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">God values man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his heart.</note> God values every man
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:100129:58"/>according to his heart, and the heart according to the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure upon which it is ſet: a wicked man is worth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe his heart is worth nothing, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.20. <hi>The heart of the wicked is little worth.</hi> God values men accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their hearts, and their hearts according to their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or the object upon which his heart is ſet. There are two things that make up the heart.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Ornaments of the heart, a meek and a quiet ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Objects of the heart, and thoſe things upon which the heart is ſet; the mans heart is worth as much as the object is that it is ſet upon, and if the object be worth nothing, the mans heart is worth nothing.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:100129:59"/>
               <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">As the heart is, ſuch is the life.</note> Ground, becauſe from the heart all the converſation flowes, therefore 'tis matter of great conſequence upon what the heart is ſet, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Keep thy heart with all diligence, for out of it are the iſſues of life, ſo out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaks, Mat.</hi> 12.34. As the heart is pure or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, ſo is the whole life: on what a mans heart is ſet, that's his treaſure, or elſe it would not bee ſo dangerous to miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place our hearts.</p>
               <p>6.<note n="6" place="margin">Objects trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the heart.</note> Its matter of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, where and upon what you ſet your hearts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the objects upon which the heart is ſet, they have a transforming power, and they doe mightily frame and faſhion the heart according to themſelves; and therefore as
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:100129:59"/>where your Treaſure is, there will your hearts be alſo, ſo like to what your Treaſure is, that will your hearts be like alſo: If a man mind nothing elſe in the world but Riches, they have nothing in their hearts but Riches, either how they may get or ſave them, if a mans heart be ſet on Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, it transforms him, and the man is ſaid to be a Covetous man, when a man either gets, or ſaves, or covets much, (for unjuſt keeping is as great an act of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs as unjuſt getting.)</p>
               <p>Jeſus Chriſt hath left one golden expreſſion, <hi>what ſhall it profit a man to gain the whole world and loſe his own ſoul?</hi> Mat. 16.26. obſerve the ſoul is not onely loſt here, but it is loſt hereafter alſo. 'Tis impoſſible
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:100129:60"/>to have the heart ſet wholly on Riches, and ſet on Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, becauſe the ſoul is fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med according to the object on which the heart is placed; therefore take theſe two things wherein the ſoul is hereby injured: In the light of it, and in the holineſſe and purity of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the light of it, let a mans heart be ſet on any heavenly beauty, its changed into a Heavenly complexion; let a mans heart be ſet on any earthly beauty, its changed into an Earthly complexion, and ſo the ſoul is loſt in the ſight of it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In the holineſſe of it: As the ſoul can ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is ſinfully evill, or ſpiritually good, when the heart is placed on wrong ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects;
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:100129:60"/>ſo it can do nothing that is ſpiritually good, nor with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand any thing that is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually evill, when 'tis placed on Earthly objects: the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and purity of the ſoul is is wronged by Earthly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; Therefore Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is called <hi>the not of all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> how comes it to be ſo? I anſwer two waies.</p>
               <p>Firſt, all evill comes from thence as the root.</p>
               <p>Secondly, all is nouriſhed by it as the root; there is no prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of evill that will not flow from this evill, and there is no evill principle that it will not nouriſh, there is no ſin that this will not frame the heart to, for it will make a man in love with every ſinne, it will make a man prove an Apoſtate from God, <hi>Demas
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:100129:61"/>hath forſaken us, having loved this preſent world,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.10. It will make a man impudent and ſhameleſs in ſin, as <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.16. <hi>What will you give me and I will betray him,</hi> faith <hi>Judas.</hi> It will make a man forget the offers of grace, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.14. and ſlight the word of God. <hi>And the Phariſees who were cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, heard all theſe things and derided him.</hi> It will make a man deſire the pleaſures of ſin that are but for ſeaſon, it will make a man ſin and deſire to ſin; you little know what hideous wrong the ſetting of the heart upon the world brings you, and what dolefull wrath it will lay you under. <note place="margin">The heart doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies follow the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> In the.</p>
               <p>Fourth Place for proof that the heart doth alwaies follow the Treaſure.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:100129:61"/>
               <p n="1">1. The heart of man hath its ſeverall motions and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goings, its Proceſſes, and its Receſſes, and all this is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the Treaſure is, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 6.9. <hi>The ſight of the Eye is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the wandrings of the deſire;</hi> 'Tis in the Hebrew, <hi>the walkings of the ſoul;</hi> then the ſoul of man is a walking thing, the heart of a man hath its outgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; It's true of the heart as it is ſaid of the Angells, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.13. they go forth with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible ſwiftneſſe like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſo doth the heart, <hi>Eccel.</hi> 11.9. there you read of the <hi>way of the heart;</hi> the heart is rendred by <hi>Montanus</hi> as a thing that is ever in motion: moſt men do make choice of their chiefe good in their youth, and their hearts go af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31. <hi>Their hearts
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:100129:62"/>go after their Covetouſneſs;</hi> their hearts walk after their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, ſo the Hebrew: you will ſay Covetouſneſſe is a ſin in the heart, how then doth the heart go after it? ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is ſpoken of Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe here as the Predominant luſt; or elſe Covetouſneſſe is put for the Object of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe on which it is ſet, hence 'tis that in Scripture the ſoul of man is made up of luſtings in a good ſence, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.15. <hi>with deſire have I deſired to eat this paſsover with you,</hi> and in an evill ſence, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.22. <hi>Put off the old man, which is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt according to the deceitfull luſt;</hi> faith the Church, <hi>draw us and we wil run after thee.</hi> Cant. 1.4. how ſo? by diſcovering the great ſweetneſs &amp; excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that are in him; are ſoules
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:100129:62"/>drawn to him, then we ſhall have a delight in fellowſhip and Communion with him, and the heart is drawn out ſutably to a mans Treaſure: here are four Demonſtrative Arguments that I ſhall give you, how it comes to paſſe that the Treaſure is attractive of the heart.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">Every unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate man hath ſome predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant luſt.</note> Every man in an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate eſtate hath ſome Predominant luſt, and this luſt is ſaid to be Predominant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the object that is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed by that luſt, there lies his Treaſure; tis called the ſtumbling block of a mans iniquity, the Fathers uſe to ſtile it a mans darling ſinne. <hi>Iob.</hi> 20.12. <hi>It is ſweet in his mouth, and he hides it under his tongue:</hi> Every ſin Rules over a man, but there are ſome ſins
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:100129:63"/>that rule more immediately then any other, and theſe ſins are a mans Treaſure, that ſin which he makes all other ſins ſubordinate to, in that he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth his chief good, and then that's the ſinne he is leaſt able to reſiſt; and what's the reaſon of it? becauſe the heart will go out after its. Treaſure, <hi>Iames</hi> 1.14. <hi>But every man is tempted, when he is drawn aſide of his wn luſt, and enticed:</hi> ſinne drawes a mans heart aſide; But remember there is no man doth periſh that ever did make a profeſſion of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but he did meet with this ſtumbling block of his darling ſin, and becauſe there was his Treaſure, his heart would go out after it. The opportunity of Temptation is when a man is tryed in his maſter luſt, hee
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:100129:63"/>cannot hold his heart from his treaſure, becauſe the treaſure hath ſuch a command and rule over the heart that he cannot reſiſt it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">The heart is impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, in purſuit of its trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> It will appeare the heart goes out to the treaſure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the purſuit of it, the heart is impatient of oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of procraſtination; of oppoſition it can beare no denyall, of procraſtination it can bear no delay, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.12. <hi>It is better to meet with a Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robbed of her whelps, then a foole in his folly:</hi> who is <hi>Solomons</hi> fool there? every wicked man that hath no fear of God, an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate man that is in his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and hath no minde to get out of it, he is a fool; I, but when is it moſt dangerous to meet with him? when he is in his folly, it is when the luſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:100129:64"/>is got up, and is ruling and raigning in the man: What's the reaſon a man had better meet a Bear robbed of her whelps, then a Foole in his folly? 'Tis becauſe you ſtand betweene the heart and the treaſure, and it can beare no oppoſition. As it can bear no denyal, ſo it can bear no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay; thus it is when covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is a mans predominant luſt; <hi>Balaam's</hi> luſt was too ſwift for his <hi>Aſs,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>They ſhall come as an Eagle doth haſten to the prey.</hi> (It is ſpoken of a covetous man) of all Birds, an Eagle flyes ſwifteſt, and never flyes ſwifter then when ſhe haſtens to eat the prey; ſo it is with every one that perſecutes his chiefeſt good whatſoever it be.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let a man change his
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:100129:64"/>Treaſure, <note place="margin">A mana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> heart changes as he changes his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> and preſently his heart changes and returnes from that which before it went out after with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt earneſtneſſe in the world, and now it returnes from it with the greateſt ſwiftneſſe: this is the firſt and the great change in Converſion, a mans changing his chiefe good, and when that is done, the ſoule returns to God.</p>
               <p>There two things that make Converſion; one is an Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the other a Converſion; the man turns away from his other treaſure, and then his heart runnes after God for his treaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.8. <hi>My ſoule followes hard after God.</hi> There are two expreſſions much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, one is, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.24. <hi>My ſervant</hi> Caleb <hi>hath followed me fully; To fulfill after the Lord,</hi>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:100129:65"/>that's the <hi>Hebrew:</hi> another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion is, <hi>To cleave unto God:</hi> the one points the ſincerity of a mans heart, and the other points the conſtancy of a mans heart; the heart that did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow ſinne and vanity, now followes after his chiefe good, becauſe he hath chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his other good for God, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.8. Ephraim <hi>ſhall ſay, what have I to doe any more with Idols?</hi> Now where the Treaſure is, there will the heart be. The Fifth Particular, <note place="margin">The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the heart goes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the treaſure.</note> is to give you the Reaſons or grounds, why the heart goes out to its treaſure: I ſhall give you ſix great grounds from that, that the treaſure is to the ſoul.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">The treaſure is the ſoules food.</note> Becauſe the treaſure is the food that the ſoule feeds on, then its no wonder the ſoule goes out after its treaſure, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:100129:65"/>cannot live without it: take an unregenerate man, he eats the treaſures of wickedneſſe, and drinks the wine of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: take a godly man, hee feeds upon ſpiritual food, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.27. <hi>Labour not or the meat that periſheth, but for the meat that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth to everlaſting life:</hi> That which is the food of the heart, the heart makes after, and cannot live without it; that's the firſt ground.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Its the ſupport of the ſoule.</note> The chiefe good is the ſupport of the ſoule, a man is not able to ſupport himſelfe without it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41.12. <hi>Thou upholdest my heart,</hi> the <hi>Hebrew</hi> is, <hi>Thou haſt underpropt my heart;</hi> the heart is not able to ſtand by it ſelfe, but the chief good holds it up; then it wants a ſupport, and this ſupport is God, <hi>Iob</hi> 8.15. There is a man
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:100129:66"/>that <hi>leanes upon his houſe:</hi> his houſe is the object of his hope, he is born up by it, and not able to ſtand without it: A Saints ſupport is onely in Gods ſtrength, <hi>My fleſh and my heart failes, but God is the ſtrength of heart and my portion for ever.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 73.26</note> Riches are an ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mans treaſure, and he runs to them to ſupport him; the name of the Lord is the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous mans treaſure, and hee runnes to it to ſupport him. Every man hath and muſt have ſomething to ſupport and defend him, and that the heart will go out after.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Its the delight of the ſoule.</note> Reaſon, why the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is attractive of the heart, becauſe it is the delight of the heart, and a man cannot live without delight; but he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have delight, but by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyring
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:100129:66"/>to his chiefe good, and there he muſt delight him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; the chiefe good is the object of the greateſt, the higheſt, the fulleſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, all its joyes come in by its chiefe good, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light the ſoul cannot live, take away all delight, and the ſoul dyes, ſaith <hi>Auſtin;</hi> therefore it muſt needs go out after the treaſure, becauſe the treaſure is the delight of the ſoul.</p>
               <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">Its the beauty of the ſoul.</note> A mans chiefe good is that wherein the beauty of the ſoule doth lye, take the ſoule off from this and its naked, becauſe the chiefe good is the beauty and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſoule, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.32. <hi>Can a Maid forget her Ornaments,</hi> ſaith God? it is intimated, God is the Ornaments and the attire of the ſoule. Take one
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:100129:67"/>whoſe chief good is in cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (that's it that beautifies the body) and he will not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily forget his attire. Can a maid? There's not a naturall impoſſibilitie of a maids for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting of her attire, and the Bride her ornaments; but there's morall impoſſibility, becauſe they are her chiefe good, and the heart goes out after them. But take a godly man now, God is the beauty and ornament of his ſoul, his glory, and chief good, and therefore his heart muſt needs go out after God. All the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orning of the ſoul is from the Treaſure, and therefore it muſt needs attract the heart.</p>
               <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">Its the breath of the ſoul.</note> The ſoul muſt go to the Treaſure, becauſe it is the breath of the ſoul, the ſoule
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:100129:67"/>ſtrangles and dies if it do not enjoy it. The Soul is alwaies breathing after the chiefeſt good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1. <hi>As the Hart pants after the water brooks, ſo my heart pants after thee O God,</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> the chief good cauſeth the breathings of the ſoul after it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Becauſe the chief good is the onely reſt of the ſoul, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 116.7. <hi>Return unto thy rest O my ſoul,</hi> the ſoul is reſtleſſe till it come to the enjoyment of him, therefore return unto thy reſt.</p>
               <p>The next thing is, <note place="margin">How the heart is carried out to its trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> how is the heart of man is carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out to his Treaſure? doth it alwaies go after it? here let me lay down theſe ſix Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</note> That the heart goes after
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:100129:68"/>the Treaſure continually, the ſoul of man is alwaies active and never idle, and what's the ground of all its motions? its the chief good, that's the ground of it, therefore the ſoul moans continually after its chief good, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.23. the wiſe man ſpeakes there of a Covetous rich man, whoſe chief good is his wealth, <hi>the heart takes no rest in the night;</hi> becauſe his heart is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally carried forth after his treaſure; the abundance of the rich will not ſuffer them to ſleep.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</note> The heart goes after the Treaſure infinitely, and unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiably, it is never ſatisfied with any thing elſe, till it be arived to its chief good: They that place their Treaſure here below, they are never ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:100129:68"/>but their hearts are going forth after it without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.6. 'tis ſaid there, <hi>they load themſelves with thick clay;</hi> A wicked man man have as much as may ſink him, but hee never hath ſo much as will ſatisfie him, they are like the horſe-leach that cries give, give; ſo a godly mans heart is alwaies gaſping after God, and going out with bounleſs deſires after Heaven.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">The heart poſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it for his own.</note> The heart taketh faſt hold of its Treaſure, and poſſeſſeth it for its own; There be other things that a man may look on as his own, but this chiefly, <hi>Iob</hi> 8.15. <hi>he ſhall take faſt hold of his houſe.</hi> Take a proud wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, her vanity is in her ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell, her apparell is her trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and how faſt will ſhee hold it? Take a covetous man
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:100129:69"/>that makes Riches his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, he takes faſt hold of his Treaſure, and will not let it goe; ſo take a man that makes God and Chriſt his treaſure, when temptations and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons come, that labour to pull a man from his treaſure; yet he laies faſt hold of it, and wil not let it go.</p>
               <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">The heart re turnes to its trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> If at any time the heart be ſhaken, yet it returnes to the chief good again. So you ſhall finde an unregenerate man that hath his treaſure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, the man is ſhaken with Afflictions, Croſſes, Troubles, Sorrowes; yet he returnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to that which he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up for his chief good; So let a godly man be ſhaken by temptations from God; yet for all that the ſoule returnes to God again, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19. <hi>I
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:100129:69"/>will return to my firſt husband,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">The change of a mans chiefe good is the firſt change.</note> The change of a mans chief good is a godly mans firſt change, and a godly mans great change, and his chiefe change. There is a change to deſtruction, <hi>they have forſaken me the Fountain of living waters;</hi> But there is a change to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and that is forſaking of <hi>broken Ciſterns</hi> for <hi>living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> do not talk of the change of Actions, but talk of this, the change of the chief good; change thy Riches for a God, thy pleaſures for a Chriſt.</p>
               <p>6.<note n="6" place="margin">In this the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and bondage of the heart lies.</note> In the chief good the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and the bondage of the heart doth lie; wherin lies the liberty of the ſoul? 'tis in this, that the ſoul is faſtned upon God as the chiefe good, and looks upon all other things in
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:100129:70"/>no other way then as they are in ſubordination unto him; when the ſoul cleaves to God, and God alone, and lookes upon all other things as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but as in ſubordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on unto him; Then, and not till then, the ſoul is at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the more thou art taken up with thy chief good, the freer thou art, for his ſervice is perfect freedome; on the contrary all men that have their Treaſures below this ſpirituall life, they are in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage continually, becauſe their treaſures are below themſelves.</p>
               <p>There is another thing wee are to open, <note place="margin">Such as the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, ſuch is the heart.</note> as the heart and the treaſure are inſeparable, that the heart will bee where the treaſure is; So ſuch as the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:100129:70"/>treaſure is, ſuch is the heart, as well as where the treaſure is there will be the heart, and ſuch as the heart is, ſuch is the man; if it belaid on Earth, then men are ſaid to be Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if laid up in Heaven, men are ſaid to be heavenly, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Your Converſation is in Heaven,</hi> though their ſoules go up and down among many Creatures; yet their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is in Heaven, for the heart of man doth cheapen here and there before itbuyes: yet notwithſtanding all is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in things below, to a man whoſe treaſure is in Earth; if a mans treaſure be in Heaven, his mind is in heaven, hence it comes to paſſe that a godly man is ſaid to be a ſtranger here, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.12. <hi>I am a ſtranger; and a Sojourner,</hi>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:100129:71"/>what's the reaſon: becauſe hee doth not converſe here as in his Country, but ſeekes a Country above, he is a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger here, travelling towards his owne Country. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, a godly mans heart is in Heaven, becauſe the Lord dwells in Heaven; hence it is that grace is called glory, not onely becauſe its of the ſame nature with that grace which a man in glory ſhal receive the the perfection of; nor onely becauſe it is a pledge and an earneſt, and will end in glory; but becauſe the ſoul immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately enters into glory after his treaſure, for his treaſure immediately being in Heaven, his heart is there; hence 'tis, a godly man is more in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then in Earth, for his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is in Heaven, and his heart is there.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:100129:71"/>
               <p>But let us ſee in particular, <note place="margin">What i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> meant by the heart.</note> what is here intended by the heart; more eſpecially there is meant all the things that are ſeated in the heart, and let's begin with the firſt of them.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">The ain and ben of the cart.</note> The heart is put for the aime, tendency, and bent of the heart, it is <hi>Animi Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> it's the propenſion of the heart, <hi>Deut.</hi> 24.15. <hi>Hee is poore and ſetteth his heart upon it;</hi> he is a hireling, and his heart is ſet upon his waies, hee doth not work for love to his maſter, nor love to his work, but the aime and bent of his ſoul is for the good hee ſhall receive by his work; therefore the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeaks of a <hi>double heart,</hi> Pſ. 12.2. what makes a heart a a double heart? ſome apply it to inſtability in opinions,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:100129:72"/>that which is called halting between two opinions, when the mind is in ſuſpence, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.20. <hi>Be not of doubtfull mindes:</hi> But whether it be in reference to opinions, or what ever it is, the mind is in doubt, and hee is double minded. But the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Scripture by a double heart doth mainly aime at the intentions of the heart, the heart goes not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies one way, but ſometimes for God, ſometimes for the Creature; ſometimes for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſometimes for Earth, when men have not a ſingle Eye, when they have not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle aimes, this the Scripture calls a double heart. When a man hath an aime at God, and the things of God, and looks it other things in ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereto, this the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:100129:72"/>calls a ſingle eye, or a ſingle heart: but when men go ſometimes very hotly after the things of God, and at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times purſue after Riches immoderately, this is a double heart, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.1. <hi>Thy heart is not right in he ſight of God:</hi> and <hi>Hab.</hi> 4.12. The word of God <hi>is the diſcerner of the intents of the heart.</hi> Now then thus, where a mans Treaſure is, there the bent, the aime, and the tendency of a mans heart is; one of the great things you are to look to, is the heart, for in the heart lyes the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt deceit, but in the heart, above all other things, the bent and tendency of the heart is that you are to looke at, and there are two Reaſons for it.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">The aime of his heart is the godly mans comfort in all failings.</note> Becauſe this is the great
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:100129:73"/>Comfort, nay the onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort that a godly man hath to flye to in all failings, and in all his falls the bent and aime of his heart; In any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar failing and infirmity, what is it the ſoul can retreat to? tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when a godly man can ſay, this hath been my tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but this was not my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, this is the onely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the man; ſo it was with <hi>Peter,</hi> it was a deſperate fall to deny his Maſter, and wiſh himſelfe accurſed that hee knew not the man; but <hi>Peter</hi> could ſay, Lord, This was the bent of my ſoule, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thee, but to die for thee. Sinne comes upon a godly man at unawares, ſinne comes upon a godly man as judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment comes upon a wicked man by way of ſurpriſall, but
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:100129:73"/>the bent of his heart was not to ſinne, therefore this is a comfort to him. 'Tis an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of <hi>David,</hi> Though he did offend with his mouth, yet I have purpoſed that my mouth ſhould not offend; it was my tranſgreſſion, but not my intention, I have plotted that my mouth might not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend; In all your failings, this is that that muſt ſupport you, yea in every tranſgreſſion, that it was not your intention ſo to do.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">It is his comfort after his failings.</note> Sometimes a godly man can take comfort in this after his fallings: many times the Saints commit wickedneſſe out of conſultation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.3. the Scripture calls them <hi>Preſumptuous ſinnes,</hi> ſinnes that they doe intend before hand, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 15.5. 'Tis ſaid, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:100129:74"/>heart was upright in all things all. he dayes of his life, ſave onely in the matter of</hi> Uriah <hi>the</hi> Hit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite. Then <hi>Davids</hi> heart was not upright in this matter, his diſſembling and his lying was clearly demonſtrated. But now what may a godly man retreat to? to the generall bent of his heart, when hee failes in a particular act, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 15.14. Nevertheleſſe <hi>Aſa</hi> his heart was upright with God all his daies; he doth not ſpeak of particular Acts, but of the generall bent of his heart, though in ſome particulars he contrived ſinne: wicked men when they are carryed on in a deſigne that's ſinfull, they will not be beaten from it, but the generall bent of their ſoul is to go on in it.</p>
               <p>Now would you know
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:100129:74"/>which way the bent and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of your heart goes, <note place="margin">Six rules for diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the bent of the heart.</note> there are ſix Rules I ſhall give you: It was the ſaying of a godly Miniſter, <hi>I bleſſe my God I have ſtadied my own heart more then Boukes;</hi> It would be very hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py for you to ſay, I have ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died my heart more then the would, more then trading.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="2" place="margin">That which its caſryed after un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, is the aime of the heart.</note> 
                  <hi>Rule.</hi> That which the ſoul is carryed after under diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent conditions, this declares what the aime and bent of the ſoule is, and ſo you muſt judge of the tendency of the heart; as waters, though you turn them out of their proper current and alter their chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, yet they all runne into the Sea, you will ſay then the tendency of them is to the Sea: If you ſee the Sun, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the day be cleare or clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:100129:75"/>it makes to the Weſt, it concludes there's the end of its courſe, this is the race it hath to runne: the going of the heart is the ſame in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent conditions, it doth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully cleave to that which is its chief good, &amp; is never at reſt til it be centered there: As for example, ſuppoſe it be the heart of a naturall man, his aime is at his owne exaltation, now pride being his predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant principle and maſter ſin; this mans pride or proſperity vents it ſelf in Exaltation, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, and ſeeking glory from men, he ſets himſelfe in the face and glory of the times, deſpiſing of others, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting himſelf: bring this man under trouble of conſcience, and then pride vents it ſelf in humility, and debaſes into
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:100129:75"/>poverty: As faith is an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling grace, ſo deſpaire is the higheſt fruit of pride, here's the heart now ſhewing the ſame aime in different condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and all this doth clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly argue, where the bent of the heart is, there's the aime of a mans heart: If a mans heart goe out to covetouſneſſe, the love of money, when he is in a low condition, if he did but obſerve his ſoule, his heart went after his covetouſneſſe; let him be brought into a weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy condition, he is ſcuſſling after the world ſtill: <hi>Judas</hi> his heart went after his money, when he was an Apoſtle, though in a different condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; take a man in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition you will, you hall find the aime and bent of his heart is ſtill the ſame. On the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary;
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:100129:76"/>take a godly man who makes God his treaſure, who hath another treaſure and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aime, put him into what condition you will, ſtill you ſhall find his aime is the ſame, the bent of his ſoule is ſtill to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.17. <hi>All this is come upon us, yet have wee not forſaken thee, nenher have we dealt falſely in thy Covenant:</hi> He looks beyond them all, for his aime is at his treaſure: Looke upon <hi>Job</hi> upon the dunghill, the aime of his heart was the ſame, <hi>fearing God, and eſchewing evill:</hi> Now conſider what you were, when you were a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man, and what you are, now you are advanced to pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of dignity, and ſee by it where the aime of your heart is.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Thats the bent of the heart which it greedily catcheth at upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions.</note> In all places &amp; in all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:100129:76"/>if opportunity be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, conſider what it is that the heart doth moſt greedily catch at upon all occaſions, and in all places: If the aime of the ſoule be luſt, <hi>he went af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her ſpeedily, as a ſoole to the correction of the Stocks Prov.</hi> 7.22. Suppoſe it be gain a mans heart aimes at, It goes after it preſently. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.21. <hi>When I ſaw a goodly Babyloniſh Garment, and two hundred ſhekles of ſilver, and a wedge of Gold, I coveted them and tooke them, &amp;c.</hi> So let there be at any time a godly motion offered to a godly man, his heart catcheth at the motion. By this you may ſee what your ſouls are, by the firſt motion you cloſe with, as according to the aime and bent of the heart, ſo all temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations are ſuited; whats that
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:100129:77"/>then which your heart cloſeth withall with the greateſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe? according to that is the bent of your heart.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the bent of the heart, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t fran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> object t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> According to the bent of heart, ſo the heart gathers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it ſelfe, whether there bee occaſions given or no, <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Every imagination of the heart is onely evill, and that continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;</hi> Imagination of the heart, it ſhould be read, <hi>Every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the heart;</hi> the heart frames to it ſelfe ſomething whether there be occaſions or no, according to the bent of it, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.16. <hi>The luſts of the ſloſh;</hi> luſt there, is put for the object of luſt, as faith is put for the object of faith, and hope for the object of hope; there is nothing tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> luſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> not make ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ther of, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:100129:77"/>
                  <hi>eyes full of adultery that cannot ceaſe from ſinne,</hi> though they have no occaſion at all, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 41.6. <hi>David</hi> Complaines, <hi>If he come to ſee me, his heart ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wickedneſſe to it ſelfe.</hi> On the contrary, take a godly man, look on the aime of his heart, here's no occaſion given at all, yet he hath ſomething the heart gathers up to it ſelf, therefore <hi>David</hi> cryes out in the middeſt of a crooked and perverſe Generation, <hi>Teach me O Lord to number my dayes, that I may apply my heart unto wiſdome;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſ. 90.1</note> as one gathers wickedneſſe, the other gathers holineſſe for the heart of man hath a ſelfe-ſufficiency in it, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.15. <hi>when luſt hath conceived it bring-eth forth ſin:</hi> luſt is ſaid to bee the Father and the Mother, able to beget and able to bring
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:100129:78"/>forth, therefore looke which way the aime goes, there the heart goes, there it centers, according to the generall bent of the heart, it gathers ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to it ſelfe, whether there be occaſion given it or no.</p>
               <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the bent, ſo it will break through alloppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</note> That's the bent of the heart, that breaks through all oppoſition to accompliſh its deſigne; the bent of the heart is ſuch a thing, that look what ever the thing be its ſet upon, though never ſo coſtly, it will ſpare no coſt to obtaine it; you that delight your ſelves in vanity of Apparell, you will ſpare no coſt to obtaine it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.6. <hi>Shechem</hi>'s heart clave to <hi>Dinah,</hi> and what doth this bring forth, <hi>Aske never ſo much dowry and it ſhall be given.</hi> Thus in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> they ſpare no coſt to laviſh away Gold for
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:100129:78"/>their Idoll Gods, becauſe the bent of their hearts was ſet upon it, you that ſtick at all coſts in Religion, and at none in Rebellion, you may eaſily ſee which way the bent of your hearts goes. If the bent of a mans heart be revenge, it will ſtick at no coſt, <hi>Haman</hi> will get the King abundance of Treaſure for the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Jewes: If the bent of the heart be for Ambition, <hi>Abſalom</hi> will not ſtick to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Father if it hinder his riſing: If it bee halting and diſſembling in Religion, <hi>Jehu</hi> will not ſtick at it to get a Kingdome; if it bee the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Merchandize of the ſouls of men, and the eſtabliſhing of <hi>Artichriſt</hi> in the Chaire of Chriſt; if it be the change of Times and Laws, if to change
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:100129:79"/>the fundamentall Laws of a Nation, if the bent of the heart beſet upon it, no oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition will hinder: So its true in reference to ſpiritual things, if the bent of a mans heart be ſet on God, no Creature op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition ſhall divert it: That's an excellent expreſſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.6. <hi>Who paſſing through the valley of</hi> Baca, <hi>make it a well:</hi> They will digge Wells in the deſart, intimating that no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition can hinder them that are fully bent to come to Chriſt: The loſſe of a right hand, the loſſe of a right eye, the soule doth not ſtick at, he will cut off the one, and pull out the other; and what's the reaſon? its all to attaine that which the bent of his soule is after.</p>
               <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">The heart is reſtleſſe untill it obtain that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which it aime,</note> Where the bent and aim
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:100129:79"/>of the heart is, there it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually reſtleſſe, untill it at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that which it tends to; the aime of the heart is <hi>Pondus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimi</hi> the weight of the ſoul; my heart pants after the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, ſo for worldly things, to <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.32. <hi>After theſe things do the Gentiles ſeeke,</hi> and they are never quiet till they find them; if it be after Knowledge, the ſoul is ſtill in a purſuite after it, and the man never gives over, but is reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, becauſe the bent of his heart goes out after it; If it be after riches, they <hi>riſe up early, go to bed late, they eat the bread of carefullneſſe;</hi> Pſ. 127.2. If it be a deſire of rule and Dominon the soule is reſtleſſe and never quiet till it gets ſome ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority in the world.</p>
               <p>6.<note n="6" place="margin">The heart makes al other things ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that, after which it aims.</note> That which is the aime
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:100129:80"/>a mans heart, hee doth make uſe of all other things to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, makes all other things ſubſervient to it: If the bent of his heart be ſet on hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God, hee cares for riches no farther then that hee may <hi>honour God with his ſubſtance,</hi> Pro. 3. 9. and ordinances no further, then in them hee may enjoy Communion with God; nay, he looks on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt no farther, then he is brought to God by him: wil the name of Religion and the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt do it? <hi>Simon Magus</hi> will buy them with money rather then hee will be without them: wil the countenance of godly men do it? then they ſhall be courted by all parties; <hi>Iehu</hi> when hee meet withs <hi>Ionadab,</hi> ſalutes him, <note place="margin">2 King. 10.15.</note> and faith, <hi>Is thy heart
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:100129:80"/>right as my heart is with thy heart?</hi> there's a doubt, doſt thou love me truly as I love thee, no man profeſſeth more ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then he whoſe trade is Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie; hee had deſtroyed the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> but it was to ſet up his owne houſe, the one was in order to the other, he was a man for Religion and reformation while Religion would ſerve his purpoſe; and he courts <hi>Ionadab</hi> to joyne with him (who was a godly man) that he might the better colour his deſign; how many are are there that are Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners of oppreſſors, and yet ſucceed them in oppreſſion? A man may be an Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of an Idolater, and yet ſucceed him in his Idolatry.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">The heart is put for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance of the heart.</note> The heart is put for the wiſdome, the ſtudies, the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:100129:81"/>plots, the contrivances of the heart: now where the heart is, there are all theſe, <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.5. <hi>O yee ſimple, underſtand wiſdom; and yee fooles be yee of an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding heart;</hi> and in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7.11. <hi>Ephraim</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>a ſilly dove without a heart.</hi> Now a man whoſe plots and deſignes are in Earth &amp; never riſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Earth, the mansplots Earthly, therefore the mans wiſdome is Earthly, <hi>James</hi> 3.15, 16. <hi>This wiſdom deſcendeth not from above, but is Earthly, Senſuall, deviliſh;</hi> if a mans treaſure be in Heaven, his wiſdom is heavenly, <hi>Iam.</hi> 3.17. <hi>But the wiſdome that is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, is pure, peaceable, gentle,</hi> &amp;c. ſo <hi>Luke</hi> 16.8. <hi>The Children of this world are ſaid to be in their Generation wiſer then the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light:</hi> There are two
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:100129:81"/>ſorts of men, and two ſorts of wiſdoms; ther's the Children of this world, and they have the wiſdom of this world; and there's the Children of light, and they have the wiſdome of another world: the one is the wiſdome that reacheth not beyond this life, the other reacheth to the life that is to come: Both theſe are wiſe in two things; in doing their own buſineſſe, and in accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing their own end; now the wiſdom of both theſe is ſeen in three things, in getting, in keeping, in encreaſing and uſing their treaſure: all the wiſdome, and deſignes, and plots of a man are exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about one or all of theſe thre ethings.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Every mans wiſdome is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in getting his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> Every mans wiſdom is exerciſed in getting his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; <hi>Amnon</hi> his luſt was his
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:100129:82"/>treaſure, and do but ſee the deviſes he found for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of it 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 13. ſo <hi>Jeroboam</hi> his aime, was to be the head of the ten tribes, &amp; ſee his wiſdome in obtaining of it, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.26. According to mans Treaſure, ſo his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and deſignes have been laid for the obtaining of it. Now a godly man, all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion that he hath attained to it, is to make him wiſe to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; A godly man hath but one deſign in the world, and that is, that he may enjoy God in Chriſt where his Treaſure is laid up; therefore <hi>Bernard</hi> well obſerves, a wiſe mans heart is with the Lord, that is, all his plots and contrivances are how he may bring about thoſe deſigns as may give him Communion with God.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">In keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his treaſure.</note> All the plots and deſigns
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:100129:82"/>in the world are how hee may keep his Treaſure; Thus it is with men here below <hi>Ier.</hi> 51, 1. The Prophet ſpeaking of men that gathered many rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, ſaith the Lord by him, <hi>I will ſend unto</hi> Babylon <hi>fanners that ſhall fan her, and ſhall empty her land;</hi> becauſe men uſe their wiſdome to keepe their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the Lord ſaith, hee will ſend fanners that ſhall take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thoſe honours and riches which they uſe ſuch meanes to keep with them, <hi>Iob</hi> 20.15. there's a man that hath <hi>ſwallowed down riches,</hi> yet in the <hi>fullneſſe of his ſufficiency he ſhall be in ſtraights,</hi> ver. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. they thought that when they had ſwallowed down riches, they ſhould never vomit them up again; but <hi>vor.</hi> 15. <hi>Hee ſhall vomit them up again</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 23. <hi>when he is about to fill his bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:100129:83"/>God ſhall cast the fury of his wrath upon him, &amp; ſhal rain is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him while he is eating:</hi> the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the men of the world is not onely how they may get their Treaſure, but how they may ſecure their treaſure. So a godly man, God in Chriſt is his Treaſure, he knowes it is ſin onely that ſeparates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and his God, and ſo his deſire is not to ſin, that he may not be ſeparated from his treaſure: A godly man hath but one neceſſity that lies upon him, and all his aime tends thereunto; and that is, that hee doth not ſinne, and thereby loſe his treaſure.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">In en creaſing and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</note> Where his Treaſure is, there is his plottings and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivings how to improve and increaſe it: a treaſure is not filled up all at once, but by
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:100129:83"/>degrees, therefore this is the great ſtudy and plot of men, how they may improve and increaſe their treaſure, <hi>Hab,</hi> 2.5. There's one deſires do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination which was his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, he looks on himſelfe, as a man born to Rule, but looks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all other men, as born to be Ruled; what doth this put him on? to increaſe his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; how doth he do it? the Text ſaith, <hi>He is a proud man, he keeps not at home, but enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his deſires as Hell, and is as death, and cannot be ſatisſied, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>thers all Nations to himſelfe:</hi> and <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.24.25. O how earneſt are men in fore-ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting devices, in contriving and plotting how to increaſe and improve their treaſure: If a mans treaſure be in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the enjoyment of God
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:100129:84"/>and Chriſt, what ever his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem is in the world, it doth not trouble him, ſo he can but go on to the obtaining of more of his treaſure. Now where your treaſure is, there is your heart, that is, there is your wiſdome, your plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and contrivings for the getting, keeping, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of it.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">The heart is put for the thoughts and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of the heart.</note> The heart is uſed for the thoughts and meditations of the heart <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.23. <hi>Trye me O Lord, and know my thoughts:</hi> there's nothing carryes the heart with it more then the thoughts; thoughts are the firſt born of the ſoule, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate iſſuings forth of the heart. The way to taſt water and not be deceived, is to caſt it at the Spring; and Wine, if you would not bee deceived
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:100129:84"/>by the Vintner, you muſt taſt it at the Wine-preſſe; ſo if you would judge aright of your hearts, you muſt look to your thoughts, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of one, that invites to dinners Now ſaith he, <hi>Eat not the bread of him that hath an evill eye, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſire thou his dainty meats: for as he thinketh in his heart, ſo is he; eat and drinke ſaith he to thee, but his heart is not with thee, Prov.</hi> 23.6, 7. what way your hearts goe, <note place="margin">Three Rules for diſcovery where your thoughts &amp; hearts are.</note> that way your thoughts go.</p>
               <p>There are three Rules that will much diſcover which way your thoughts goe; and by theſe you will know where your hearts are, and by that where your treaſure is.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Whither doe your thoughts retyre when you ar alone.</note> When you are alone ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred from company, out of worldly imployment; whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:100129:85"/>then do your thoughts u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually retyre? for the man i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> as he is alone, ſuch as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thought is, ſuch is the man: Take a godly man, would you know where his thoughts are when he is in his Cloſet in his bed? <hi>when I awake ſaith</hi> David, <hi>I am ſtill with thee, early in mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning will I direct my prayer to thee, and will look up,</hi> Pſal. 5.3.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">What are theſe thoughts in which you finde the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſweetneſs</note> Rule, by which your thoughts may be diſcovered, and you may judge where your hearts are, is this; what are thoſe thoughts that you uſe to find the greateſt ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and delight in? <hi>Pſa.</hi> 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.17. <hi>How precious are thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> unto me O God! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> great is the ſumme of them!</hi> To one man the thought of his lefts are ſweet, and he acts over his wickedneſſe in a contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:100129:85"/>way with delight, and the thoughts of God are bitter unto him, and trouble him; there's no ſweetneſſe in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon God to a wicked man, and there's nothing but ſweetneſſe in the thoughts of God to a godly man.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">What thoughts are of longeſt continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with you.</note> Rule, What thoughts are they, that are of longeſt continuance with you, that your ſoules doe moſt abide upon, the thoughts that abide in your ſoules moſt, diſcover where your hearts are? <hi>Jer.</hi> 4.19 <hi>How long ſhall vaine thoughts abide in you?</hi> Pſal. 10.4. <hi>God is not in all his thoughts;</hi> nay God is not in his thoughts at at all: what do your thoughts ſtay on? Take a naturall man, and caſt in ſome thoughts of his treaſure, his thoughts will abide there; but caſt in any
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:100129:86"/>thought of heaven, and thoſe dye preſently as a fiſh out of its element. Then examine your thoughts when you are alone, what thoughts come into your mind and abide up on your ſpirits, for your trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is as the meditation of your thoughts and hearts are.</p>
               <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">The heart is put for the love and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the heart.</note> The heart is put for the love and affections of the heart, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 5.9. <hi>My heart is towards the Governours of Iſrael that offered themſelves willingly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people:</hi> Its <hi>Deborah</hi>'s ſpeech. The people of God love all that are imployed for God, and the more men are imployed for God, the more their hearts are drawn out after them. The heart of man is ſaid to be where it loves, rather then where it lives; now the heart is here taken
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:100129:86"/>properly for the loves of the heart, ſo where the heart is, there's the Treaſure.</p>
               <p>Now how ſhould a man know where his love is ſet? 'Tis a thing of marvellous great conſequence to conſider where a man ſets his love, <note place="margin">Its a thing of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment where a man ſets his love.</note> and upon what his love is fixed; And this is the maine of this Text, and there are 4 grounds why 'tis a thing of ſo great Concernment, where a man ſets the loves of his heart.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Becauſe a mans love is his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt gift.</note> Becauſe a mans love is his greateſt gift, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe a gift indeed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out love, but love is a gift of it ſelfe, though there be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe. It's ſo if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the love of God, though the Lord have not given you any thing, if he doth but ſet his love upon you, its a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er gift then Heaven or Earth
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:100129:87"/>could be: ſo likewiſe the Lord Jeſus Chriſt if he had not given us intereſt in his victories, in his ſonſhip, in his priviledges, ſo hee had given us but his love, it was a greater gift then heaven or earth, ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.1. <hi>If I had all things, and had not Charity, it profiteth nothing;</hi> Hypocrits ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times give God great gifts, but they reſerve their love, ſo God gives many of them great gifts but he reſerves his love for the ſaints; ſo that love is the greateſt gift that a man hath from God, and 'tis the great eſt gift a man can give to God.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">He that gives his love, gives himſelf.</note> Becauſe he that gives his love, he gives himſelf, he gives all things elſe whatſoever hee hath; That's pure and free love indeed that gives all things to the perſon beloved: the Lord ſets his love upon
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:100129:87"/>his people from all eternity, and when hee purpoſeth to give all things, hee gave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, love firſt gives it ſelf, and then all things elſe, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.7. <hi>he that overcommeth ſhall inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit all things,</hi> how ſo? <hi>I will be his God, and be ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll be my Son;</hi> So tis with men, he that gives his love, gives all things, and hee that withholds his love withholds all things, for a mans love Commands all that he hath; Therefore 'tis a mighty thing to conſider where a man ſets his love.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">A mans love maks the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> loved his own.</note> A mans love is that which makes the thing beloved his own. A learned man ſaith, God is our owne above all things we call ours: Eſtate is ours, and friends are ours, but God is more ours then they, becauſe he loves us more then they. 'Tis by the love of God
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:100129:88"/>that we come to be his, by our love to God that he comes to be ours. Its our love that makes the thing beloved ours, thou canſt call nothing thine but what thou loveſt.</p>
               <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">Its a mans love that ſets the price upon all things.</note> It's a mans love that ſets the price upon all things. Great things are of ſmall value where love is wanting, and ſmall things are of great value where love is preſent; its ſo with God, and ſo with the Saints. If God give to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men the greateſt heaps of Gold in the world, how do the Saints value this? 'tis but a bone caſt to the doggs, why ſo? becauſe there is no love in it; ſo likewiſe let a godly man give but to God a ſmall thing, there is love in it, and indeed that love raiſeth the price, the poor widow caſt in
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:100129:88"/>but <hi>two mites,</hi> Luke 21.12. it was with more love and affection then others, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore more in acceptance.</p>
               <p>What ſhould a man ſet his love upon, that by this means he may know where his heart is? All love is lovely where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it is, and to be bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oved, even naturall love, God loves all his Creatures, and all pure love ſhould be ſet upon him, <hi>Mark.</hi> 10.21. <hi>He that loves Father and Mother more then me, is not worthy of me.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may we not love that which is good? Yes, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe: As all truths are to be known and be believed, ſo all good things are to bee embraced and loved, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.37. <hi>He that hates not Father and Mother &amp;c. cannot be my Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> To love Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:100129:89"/>is a duty; but you ſee what it is that muſt have the chiefe place of your love; <hi>10.</hi> 12.35. <hi>He that loves his life more then me,</hi> and my truth, and my wayes, this man <hi>is not worthy of me,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.15. <hi>He that loves the world, the love of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is not in him.</hi> Is it not lawfull to love the world, and the things of the world? Yes, but not more then me. To love the Creature more then God, is that which makes it luſt; To love the Creature in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination to God, is that which makes it love: Then what is that which you love moſt? would a man know where his love is, there is trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is.</p>
               <p>And becauſe this is the main thing in the Text, <note place="margin">Rules <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> know where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ur love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are.</note> I ſhall give you eight things to know
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:100129:89"/>where your hearts are, and where your treaſure is.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">What is it you do eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially deſire u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with.</note> What is that you doe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially deſire union with? for love is an affection that carries an affectionate tenden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to union, and this will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare if you obſerve the love of God; Union with God is firſt in Gods intention, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is laſt in his executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the people of God in glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry are brought into two things</p>
               <p n="1">1. Into an immediate viſion of him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Into the cloſeſt union with him. There is a two-fold union. 1. Is generall of all the Creatures to God, that's the union of Dependance, <hi>In him me live, and move, and have our being, Act.</hi> 17.28. They can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live ſeparate from God, becauſe he is the life of them.
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:100129:90"/>2. There's a ſpeciall union peculiar to the Saints, which is the indwelling of God in them, and their indwelling in God; ſuch an union none but the Saints have by the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God in their ſoules. God loves the Saints, and his love carries a tendency to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; Jeſus Chriſt loved his people, and he ſeekes alwayes to become one with them. There is a natural union which is by conſtitution; there is an union of likeneſs &amp; fruition, a union of ſimilitude, &amp; there is an union of enjoyment, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. <hi>They that are joyned to the Lord, are one ſpirit,</hi> the Greeke ſignifies, <hi>they are glewed to the Lord:</hi> If a man love God, he is glewed to God; where a mans love is, there the ſoule goes after the thing beloved to be united: If a man love
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:100129:90"/>God, then the heart followes hard after God and all, that it may be made one with him; to this end, you have two Metaphors remarkable in ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, one is in <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.9. There <hi>Nimrod</hi> is called a <hi>mighty hunter before the Lord;</hi> It is an expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſet forth the purſuite of the ſoule after a thing: A godly man is a mighty hunter after God, his ſoul purſues af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God continually. I read a ſtory of one that was going in haſt, one asked him whither he was going? he ſaid, he was going to hunt after God. The other Metaphor, is the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize &amp; trading for Chriſt and grace in the things of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and he that trades for Chriſt and grace, is called a <hi>Merchant-man, Mat.</hi> 13.45. &amp; in a <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. A worldly man is
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:100129:91"/>called a <hi>Merchant,</hi> hee doth wholly trade for things below. Now obſerve what's your trade; if thy trade be for Jeſus Chriſt, and the things of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, then there's thy love: What is that you purſue after and deſire union with? accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your purſuit, ſo is your loves, and acording to your loves, ſo is your treaſure.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Love moves the ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the nearer it comes to the thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved.</note> The neerer love comes to the thing beloved, the ſwifter it moves towards it; the nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer a mans love comes to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the thing hee loves, the ſwifter he moves after it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.10. <hi>If Riches encreaſe, ſet not your hearts upon them:</hi> wicked covetous men, the richer they are, the more their heart is ſet on riches, the more miſerable, and griping, and ſcraping they are to get their treaſure; why
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:100129:91"/>ſo? becauſe the nearer that love comes to the thing belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the ſwifter it moves after it. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>God puts his love into betrothed perſons;</hi> what's the reaſon of that? becauſe there muſt be a time between the betrothing and the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, that the deſire may be kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled ſo much the more: The nearer a man comes to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of anything he loves, the more vehemently his heart is carryed after it. Now if it be ſo, examine by this Rule, the more you have of God and of Chriſt, the more do your hearts runne after them, the more you have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Chriſt, the more your hearts act towards him with the greateſt impatiency.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> love is is bou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiful.</note> Love is bountifull, and where ever thy bounty is, there
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:100129:92"/>is thy love; for where a man ſhews moſt bounty, there cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly is moſt love. Acts of the greateſt bounty, are demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of the higheſt love, for love opens the heart, and that opens the hand; God loves you, and becauſe he can give you no greater gift, hee gives you himſelfe; he loves us, therefore he gives his Son to us. Men may think ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Miniſters ſpeak for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate reſpects; alas! 'tis to prove the ſincerity of your love the more: Tell me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where your bounty is laid out; if your bounty be laid out about feaſting your bellies, or cloathing your backs, there your love is: Is thy bounty towards God? As he that loves his belly, thinks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to much for it; ſo he that
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:100129:92"/>loves his God, thinks nothing too much for God, thinks no pains too much that he layes out for God: ſo <hi>Haman</hi> loves his revenge, and he will give the King much for the ruine of the Jews. <hi>David</hi> when he came to build the Temple, thought he could never ſpend enough about the Temple; It is a large heart that makes an hand, therefore where your love is, there's your bounty.</p>
               <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">Love is labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> Love is laborious, it grudgeth no pains, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10. It is called the <hi>labour of love;</hi> a mans labour is ſutable to his love, he that labors moſt, loves moſt. If a man loves riches, he labours for them, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.13. Labouring in vain, is called, <hi>labouring in the fire:</hi> you ſhall know where your love is by your labour, <hi>Eccle.</hi>4.8. There's
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:100129:93"/>a man <hi>hath no end of all his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour;</hi> why ſo? There's his love, <hi>His eye is not ſatisfied with Riches:</hi> The Lord Jeſus Chriſt his love to his Father, made him la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the worke of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, till he had <hi>ſpent his ſtrength</hi> and dryed up his radicall hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.4. For a man that's ſloathful, there's no love in him, lazy love is pretended love; where love is according to the degree of it, ſuch a mans labour will be. O you that are dead and dull in holy duties, ſtrengthen your love, and you will mend your pace. Its an obſervation of one of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, That love that doth not put forth it ſelfe to its ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavour, is unſound love; that which goes to its ſtrength and no more, that's true love, but weake love;
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:100129:93"/>ſtrong love bends to impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilities, it will labour in thoſe things which 'tis impoſſible to obtain. It's obſerved of <hi>Mary,</hi> her love out-bid her ſtrength; therefore examine where the great labour of your lives hath been, how much have I labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the things of this world, and how little have I laboured for the things of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, for God, &amp; Chriſt.</p>
               <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">Love is ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note> Would you know where your love is? love is ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, it will hazard any thing for the thing beloved; our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt gives you an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of it, he doth not onely venture his life, but lay down his life; <hi>Greater love hath no man then this, that a man lay down his life for his friend,</hi> Ioh. 15.13. and Pſal. 69.9. <hi>The reproach of them that reproached thee, hath fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:100129:94"/>upon me.</hi> It was a gracious ſpeech of an Ancient, <hi>If the Lord make uſe of me to keepe off re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach from himſelfe, I ſhall looke upon it as a great priviledge, as a great honour.</hi> Where is the man, that for the truths of God and Chriſt, will hazard the loſſe of friends, the loſſe of his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, the loſſe of his blood? True love turns cowardize in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to courage; the Hen, though but a feeble Creature, yet will hazard her ſelfe againſt the moſt ravenous Birds that come to devour her Chickens; ſo will the mother, if her child be in danger. Take a man whoſe love is ſet on luſt, and what will not the man hazard for it? he will loſe his friends, he will ſpend his eſtate, he will blaſt his reputation, he will hazard his ſoule, and all for
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:100129:94"/>the love he beares to ſin: and indeed what's that which makes men deſpiſe the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God? it's their love to ſin: then enquire and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine your ſelves, where your adventures are, there is your love.</p>
               <p>6.<note n="6" place="margin">Love is zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</note> Love is zealous; I doe not mean by zeale, a zeale of ſuſpition of evill in the party beloved which we call jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy, for <hi>love thinks no evill,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. But when I ſay love is zealous, I meane, it is full of ſolicitude, fearing that any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie or wrong ſhould be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to the perſon or thing beloved. <hi>Moſes,</hi> the meekeſt man upon earth, yet <hi>Moſes</hi>'s meekneſſe is turned into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, when wrong is done to the God of his life, and the God of his love, and he breaks
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:100129:95"/>the Tables. The Lord Jeſus Chriſt out of love to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaith, <hi>The zeal of thy houſe hath eaten me up, Iob.</hi> 2.17. Zeal in the heart is like boiling wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that waſts in the ſeething, it makes a man over-look all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, conſidering himſelfe in the world, to be wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to carry on the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts of the party belove. So it is with godly men, for zeale is a mixt affection, 'tis nothing elſe but love provoked: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Hoſter</hi> ſpeaks the language of love; <hi>How ſhould I endure to ſee the evil that ſhould come upon me and upon my people, Eſt.</hi> 8.6. Tel me, what are you zealous for? where's your zeale? Touch a man in his Reputation, and you may quickly ſee where his love and zeal is; touch God in his name, &amp; Chriſt in his truth,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:100129:95"/>then ſaith <hi>Paul, To whom we gave place, no not for an houre, that the truth of the Goſpel might continue with you, Gal.</hi> 2.5. Love is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked with any thing, and comes contrary to Chriſt and his truth; I would have zeale to be turned into fire, and ſo it will be, (where love is) for God and his glory. Examine therefore what it is, that makes you hot on every occaſion; where thy zeal is, there is thy love, for love is zealous.</p>
               <p>7.<note n="7" place="margin">Love i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fearful of ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Love is very fearful of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the thing belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it deſires nothing more then union, it fears nothing more then ſeparation; its the Spouſes expreſſion, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.4. <hi>When I ſound him, I held him, and would not let him go. Auſtin</hi> gives that as the difference, between true and uncleane love, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:100129:96"/>the love of a Wife, and the love of a Harlot, both fear the husband, but the one fears leſt the husband ſhould come, the other fears leſt the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ſhould depart; the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the ſoule in this way are ſeen very much Death is called the King of terror, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe its a ſeparation of the ſoule from the body; love, it loves union, and he that loves, dyes himſelfe to live in the thing beloved; for this cauſe, the great conſolation of the Saints, lies in this, <hi>who ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate us from the love of God &amp; c? Rom.</hi> 8.30, 31. For in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the love of the thing beloved, the heart languiſhes: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n union with the thing loved, the heart rejoyces, and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the thing loved, the heart dyes and periſhes; for
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:100129:96"/>this cauſe, is this the great cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial to the Saints, that there is no ſeparation between their love, and their beloved. The unhappineſſe of wicked men lies in this, that they love that which ſhall be ſeparated from them; <hi>Riches make to themſelves wings &amp; flie away, P, o.</hi> 23.5. And thou fool, this night ſhall thy ſoul be taken away from thee, and then <hi>whoſe ſhall theſe things be? Luk.</hi> 12.20. So <hi>Amos</hi> 4.2. <hi>I will take away thy poſterity with fiſh-hooks:</hi> As eaſily as the fiſh is drawn out of the water with a hooke, ſo will I take them away with <hi>Fiſh-hooks.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when an ungodly man dies, his love dies, becauſe his beloved ceaſeth when he dies: A godly man, becauſe he ſhall never be ſeparated from the thing beloved, his love ſhall
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:100129:97"/>continue for ever in heaven, and he ſhall never be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from it. Then examine your ſelves, that which you feare to be ſeparated from, is that which the love of your heart runs out unto.</p>
               <p>8.<note n="8" place="margin">Love is victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note> Love is victorious, <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.4. <hi>'Tis strong as death;</hi> there's a kind of dominion in love, looke over the love that men bear to the things of this life, let them have but Riches, and if Chriſt, and the glory of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven be tendered to them, as the young man had in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and bid them ſell all, they will go away ſorrowful; why ſo? the love of the world o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercomes them. On the other ſide, offer a godly man all the comforts of this life whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver his heart could wiſh, yet notwithſtanding he doth not
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:100129:97"/>imbrace it; why ſo? his love to God out-bids them, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercomes them. Love, it is like Lime, in that reſpect <hi>many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cannot quench love, Cant.</hi> 8.7. Nay the more you pou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e upon lime, the hotter it burns. Its not onely faith that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the world, but love o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercomes the world, for love is a victorious Grace as well as Faith. If you be offered great things in this world, greater things in another world doth overcome them: therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine where your love is, for where your love is, ther's your heart; where your heart is, there's your Treaſure; where your Treaſure is, there's your Heaven, where your Heaven is, there's your God; and where your God is, there's your happineſſe.</p>
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:100129:98"/>
               <p>There are onely three ſhort uſes I ſhall make, and ſo ſhut up the point.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 1. <note place="margin">1. <hi>Uſe.</hi>
                  </note> Shall be in generall in two things.</p>
               <p>1. <note place="margin">To diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the fulneſſe that is in every ſcripture ſentence.</note> From hence ſee the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Scripture, every ſhort ſentence of it, how full of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is it? the ſmalleſt things in Scripture there, are great things depending on them, therefore a Father cryes out in admiration of the fulneſſe of the Scripture: Its obſerved by <hi>Chryſostome,</hi> he ſaith, Its the greateſt Blaſphemy that can be, to think that in the Booke of God there ſhould be found one idle word: hee that will judge you for idle words, will not write one idle word. There's one place which <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostome</hi> himſelf inſiſts upon, its 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.23: <hi>Drink no longer wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:100129:98"/>but uſe a little wine for thy ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks, ake;</hi> and he hath eight mighty truths out of that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary portion of Scripture.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Godly men out of love to duty, neglect the body.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Godly men are very mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in the uſe of the creatures, left they ſhould be brought under the power of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider in his weakneſs hee did not ceaſe from his charge, he had infirmities, and often infirmities, but he did not neglect the affaires of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Take a little wine:</hi> That godly men may too far neglect their bodies, even to offend therin.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Every creature of God is good in it ſelf; yea, thoſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God that are moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Godly men may be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:100129:99"/>to many bodily infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and that often.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In the decay of nature, the Creatures are to be uſed for its repair; but according to the proportion of natures infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p n="8">8. There's a moderation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in receiving the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, even when men take them for neceſſities ſake, for he that preſcribes him the wine, preſcribes him the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: upon this accompt, the Scripture becomes exceeding ſweet to a man; and 'tis a great Argument of growth of grace in him, and of profiting in ſpirituall knowledge when a man can take delight and ſweetneſſe in the word, not onely in the ſubſtance, but in every circumſtance of it. Do not ſtudy the ſubſtance of the
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:100129:99"/>word onely, but the phraſe of it: they are not only words, but ſuch words as God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath choſen out, &amp; phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to our minds, and to our underſtandings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">There are ſome ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of ſcripture that we ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially treaſure up.</note> Conſider, though all the Scripture be to be ſtudied, yet there are ſome ſentences above all, that a man, ſhould lay up in his heart; ſuch as theſe we are ſpeaking on, <hi>Where a mans Treaſure is, there will his heart be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are fix parts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the Lord puts ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall marks upon, which ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ſutable to eſpeciall occaſions, and therefore wee ſhould take eſpecial notice of them.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Such as the Lord hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded anote of atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto.</note> Thoſe ſcriptures which the Lord hath added a note of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and aſſeveration to, thoſe eſpecially we ſhould ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die;
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:100129:100"/>
                  <note place="margin">Io. 1.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold the Lambe of God that takes away the ſinnes of the world:</hi> Where the Lord doth put ſpecial marks upon them, there we ſhould exerciſe a ſpeciall ſtudy about them; <note place="margin">Iſa. 40.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold, the glory of the Lord ſhall be revealed, and all fleſh ſhall ſee it, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">Such as are of ten re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated.</note> Such ſcriptures as the Lord hath often repeated, ſuch ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures ſhould bee diligently ſtudied; <hi>As Riches profit not in the day of wrath;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 11.4 Mark. 8.36.</note> And <hi>what ſhal it profit a man to gain the whole world and loſe his own ſoul?</hi> And <hi>if Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches increaſe, ſet not your hearts upon them,</hi> Pſa. 62.10.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">Such as have bin moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall for your conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> Thoſe ſcriptures that God hath made uſe of in a ſpeciall manner to doe you, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good, theſe ſhould bee mightily ſtudied, God requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers you ſhould take notice of them in a ſpeciall manner; ſo
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:100129:100"/>did the Ancients, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. And <hi>Luther</hi> made uſe of <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. and <hi>Junius,</hi> of <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.1. Thoſe by which the Lord hath ſpoken Conviction and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, theſe he requires you ſhould eſpecially obſerve, and diligently ſtudy.</p>
               <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">Such are ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</note> Thoſe ſcriptures that ſpeak eſpecially concerning thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, the Lord requires a man ſhould ſtudy that word, that is ſutable to his eſtate, whether thou art in poverty or riches, in health or ſickneſs.</p>
               <p>5.<note n="5" place="margin">Such as ſpeak to the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies of the times</note> Thoſe Scriptures that ſpeak to the preſent contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie of the Age that you live in, that you may be eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth, and keep from falling into the preſent errors; the Lord requires you to be much in the ſtudy of theſe Scriptures.</p>
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:100129:101"/>
               <p>6.<note n="6" place="margin">Such as are moſt compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive.</note> Thoſe ſcriptures that are very comprehenſive, that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in them the guidance of a mans life; as in the Text, <hi>Lay up for your ſelves treaſures in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, &amp;c.</hi> and that <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Be convent with ſuch things as you have, for he hath ſaid, I will never leave thee nor forſake thee:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.14.</note> And <hi>without holineſſe, no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> Such comprehenſive directions as theſe the Lord requires our hearts ſhould be exerciſed in the ſtudy of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Uſe</hi> 2. To dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the neceſſity regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Is moſt proper in this point: Is the heart inſeparable from the treaſure? Then this ſhews to every unregenerate man, that there is an abſolute neceſſity of Regeneration. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a carnall man will com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, and fay, I cannot bow my thoughts God-ward; what commands my thoughts? Thy
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:100129:101"/>treaſure commands them. If thy treaſure be in God, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of thy heart will be towards God. What is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion? 'Tis a change of a mans chief good; Thy treaſure and thy heart will be changed together, change thy treaſure, and thy heart will change. <note place="margin">The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of that man whoſe treaſure is on earth.</note> The miſery of that man whoſe heart is on earth, is unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, becauſe then his treaſure is on earth. Conſider theſe things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let thy Actions be what they will, if thy treaſure be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, thy heart will be below: A temporary man may and will goe forth in temporary actions more then a ſpirituall man can do: But in a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary man there's no change of heart. <note place="margin">Act, 8.21</note> 
                  <hi>Simon Magus</hi> he waſhed his hands, but kept his heart
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:100129:102"/>in the ſame blackneſſe of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs that it was before; Till thou change thy treaſure, thy heart will never change. The miſery of an ungodly man is in this, he may change his love when he will, but his heart is not changed unleſſe his treaſure be changed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This is the ground of the greateſt bondage to an ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man in the world, becauſe his treaſure is below, therefore his heart cannot be above; for where his Treaſure is, there will the heart be. This is that which keeps all unregenerate men in bondage; there is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an abſolute neceſſity for the change of a mans treaſure, or otherwiſe thou canſt not be aſſured that thy heart is changed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Uſe.</hi> 3. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Uſe</hi> 3.</note> Learn then the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:100129:102"/>condition of a godly man, <note place="margin">To diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the bleſſed condition of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man whose treaſure is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</note> he is every where bleſſed; his body is on earth, but his heart is in heaven. There's a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold bleſſing upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt</hi> Let this man at any time go aſtray (for a godly man is apt to wander) this will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and bring him home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the heart will be to the Treaſure: A godly man can never fall from God, why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the heart and the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure are inſeparable: As the miſery of an ungodly man is, let him profeſſe what he will, yet his treaſure will bring him back; ſo a godly man, let him wander whither he will, yet his treaſure will reduce him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> He is a happy man that hath his treaſure alwaies in Heaven; he is a happy man,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:100129:103"/>becauſe he is a heavenly man, his heart is in heaven. There are four Reaſons, why he that hath his Treaſure alwaies in Heaven, is a happie man.</p>
               <p>1.<note n="1" place="margin">Here by he is eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to be an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly man.</note> Becauſe hereby he is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced to be a heavenly man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.48. <hi>As is the earthly, ſuch are they that are earthly; and as is the heavenly, ſuch are they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that are heavenly:</hi> Becauſe thy heart is in heaven, therefore thou art a heavenly man: As that wiſdome that is conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant about earth, is ſaid to be earthly, ſo that wiſdome that is converſant about heaven, is ſaid to be heavenly. An earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mind is a plague, an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly mind is a glory.</p>
               <p>2.<note n="2" place="margin">His heart doth not change with his conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> He that hath his treaſure in heaven is a bleſſed man, in this, that his heart is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to thoſe impreſſions of
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:100129:103"/>changes that other means are. It a mans condition doth change, yet if his heart doth not change, its no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> obſerves, though he was under great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions on earth, yet his heart was out of danger, becauſe it was in heaven; therefore <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.6. Saints <hi>are ſaid to dwell in heaven;</hi> the heart changes not for any evil, becauſe its bound up in an unchangeable good.</p>
               <p>3.<note n="3" place="margin">His con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation will be in heaven.</note> He is a happy man, who hath his Treaſure alwaies in Heaven; becauſe where his treaſure is, there will his heart and converſation bee, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Our converſation is in Heaven, from whence alſo wee looke for our Saviour the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ.</hi> Saith the wiſe man, <hi>Keep thy heart with all diligence, for out of it are the iſſues of life,
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:100129:104"/>Prov.</hi> 4.23. The way of his life comes out of his heart. Now this man taking up of his heart with God, muſt have his life taken up with God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; he is taken up with God as his Father, with Chriſt as his husband, with the Saints and bleſſed Spirits as his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions.</p>
               <p>4.<note n="4" place="margin">His ſoul ſhall ſhortly be there.</note> A mans heart being in heaven, his ſoule ſhall ſhortly be there too. And this alſo is an argument, that bodies ſhall be there ſhortly; for though bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule be parted by death, yet it will not be long before they are united again; and what a comfortable thing is this then, for a man to lay up his Treaſure in Heaven, ſeeing it is ſuch an argument that he himſelfe ſhall be taken up into Heaven.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
